<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Brendan Ritchie</title>
 <link href="https://bhritchie.github.pages/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://bhritchie.github.pages/"/>
 <updated>2014-11-23T09:31:50-05:00</updated>
 <id>https://bhritchie.github.pages</id>
 <author>
   <name>Brendan Ritchie</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Svataḥ Prāmāṇya in Kumārila Bhaṭṭa</title>
   <link href="https://bhritchie.github.pages/2014/11/19/svatah-pramanya-in-kumarila-bhatta/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://bhritchie.github.pages/2014/11/19/svatah-pramanya-in-kumarila-bhatta</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;abstract-label&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/kumaarila/&quot;&gt;Kumārila Bhaṭṭa&lt;/a&gt;, an influential Indian philosopher of the 8th century, argues that beliefs are &lt;em&gt;svataḥ prāmāṇya&lt;/em&gt; (generally glossed as ‘intrinsically valid’). This has often been understood to mean, both clasically and by contemporary writers, to amount to the unpromising view that all beliefs are true, or alternatively that all beliefs are justified. I defend a more sympathetic interpretation according to which Kum=arila claims that beliefs are presumptively justified, the grounds for this claim being that other understandings of epistemic justification entail vicious justificatory regress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction-the-mmms-inquiry-into-dharma&quot;&gt;Introduction: The Mīmāmsā Inquiry into Dharma&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pūrva Mīmāmsā was first of all a school of exegesis. The great bulk of their founding text—the &lt;em&gt;Mīmāmsā Sūtra&lt;/em&gt;, set down in the 1st or 2nd century AD and credited to one Jaiminī—treats interpretative difficulties in the Vedas, discusses their study, and details rules for settling procedural questions regarding sacrificial ritual. But by the first century, the heyday of ritual was already long past, and there was much skepticism as to whether Mīmāmsā’s constitutive aim—according to &lt;em&gt;MS&lt;/em&gt; I.i.1 the inquiry into &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;—was best pursued in the Mīmāmsā fashion. There were rival religious traditions: Buddhists and Jains, as well as the plainly nihilistic Cārvākas. And there were rival schools of Vedic exegesis, and many Hindus who, though acknowledging the authority of the Vedas, attributed them to gods—unlike the atheistic Mīmāmsākas, who claimed that the scriptures had simply always existed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it would have seemed appropriate to establish some philosophical foundation for the school. And indeed several epistemological theses are set out in the first chapter of the &lt;em&gt;Mīmāmsā Sūtra&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MS&lt;/em&gt; I.i.4. Perception is knowledge which one has by the senses coming in contact with the soul. It is not the cause of duty [&lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;] by reason of acquiring knowledge of the thing existing.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian texts are characteristically cryptic. Pithily rendered verses are meant to be committed to memory and elucidated orally by teachers, or studied with the aid of commentaries. And the &lt;em&gt;Mīmāmsā Sūtra&lt;/em&gt; is difficult even by these standards. The verse is obviously invoking some psychological theory—though written around the 1st century, the &lt;em&gt;MS&lt;/em&gt; codifies ideas of much great antiquity.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But we must be satisfied—as Mīmāmsākas of later generations themselves had to be—with the text itself and the only slightly less difficult 5th-century commentary of Śābara.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless the import of the verse is reasonably clear (and this will follow Śābara). For Mīmāmsākas, &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; concerns a causal system relating actions and future outcomes, so that to perceive &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; would be to perceive the future. And this verse points out that sense perception makes contact only with what exists in the present. So one cannot learn about &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; through perception (as the Buddha was purported to have done).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, happily, &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; is attested to by the Vedas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MS&lt;/em&gt; I.i.5. Certainly there is eternal connection between the word and its meaning; its knowledge is injunction; it is never erroneous in matters invisible; it is authoritative in the opinion of Bādarāyana&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; by reason of its not depending on others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is yet more puzzling than the previous verse, and Śābara offers little more than a paraphrase.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We seem to be presented with the claim that testimony (i.e. Vedic testimony) is infallible with regard to “matters invisible” (specifically &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The reason for this is, apparently, that Vedic testimony about &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; does not depend upon “others”: it does not ultimately rely on any of the other legitimate sources of knowledge catalogued by Śābara.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In other words, testimony, which in the ordinary case—and Mīmāmsā joins every other Indian school on this point—can only convey knowledge which was originally acquired in some other way, is, in the special case of &lt;em&gt;dharmic&lt;/em&gt; knowledge, an infallible authority, precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; no other means of acquiring knowledge will do the job. And thus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MS&lt;/em&gt; I.i.2. Duty is a purpose having injunction for its sole authority.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we don’t have much idea how these ideas might have been fleshed out in the earlier centuries of the Mīmāmsā school. We ought also to allow for the distance between ourselves and these medieval atheistic scriptural exegetes who take the authorless but eternal and transcendent texts of the Hindu Vedas as the only possible authority for their ritualistic morality. (Though atheists do still walk among us.) We note in particular an astonishingly ‘atemporal’ Indian attitude towards literature in general. Thus&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;we can read thousands of pages of Sanskrit on any imaginable subject and not encounter a single passing reference to a historical person, place, or event—or at least to any that, historically speaking, matters.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that language has a natural or eternal status seems indeed to have been anticipated in earlier grammatical texts.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The &lt;em&gt;Mīmāmsā Sūtra&lt;/em&gt;’s bold epistemology of &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; is somewhat more intelligible given such facts and the attendant conceptions of the cosmos and our place therein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidently this doesn’t vindicate Mīmāmsā epistemology. Nor were the philosophers of other Indian schools much impressed. There can still be little wonder, then, if even one of the most serious and sympathetic recent scholars of Indian philosophy has found in this aspect of Mīmāmsā “a kind of fundamentalism.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter Kumārila Bhatta, a 7th century Mīmāmsāka. His &lt;em&gt;Ślokavārtika&lt;/em&gt;, comprising well over three thousand verses, corresponds to just the first thirty-two verses of the &lt;em&gt;Mīmāmsā Sūtra&lt;/em&gt;—i.e. those verses which had set out the philosophical basis of Mīmāmsā. In this paper we are primarily concerned with the second chapter of the &lt;em&gt;Ślokavārtika&lt;/em&gt;—the &lt;em&gt;Codanāsūtra&lt;/em&gt;, or chapter on injunction—which is framed as a commentary on &lt;em&gt;MS&lt;/em&gt; I.i.2.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Kumārila defends the authority of the Vedas on matters of &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; by way of a quite general epistemological thesis, the ‘&lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt;,’ or ‘intrinsic validity’ thesis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CS&lt;/em&gt; 47–8. The validity of all valid cognitions is to be understood as intrinsic, since a potency not existing intrinsically cannot be brought about by something else.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kumārila is claiming that “cognition” (‘&lt;em&gt;jñāna&lt;/em&gt;’ approximates to ‘occurrent judgment’) is (in some way) epistemically legitimate by default, or immediately. This will ultimately support the authority of the Vedas, since the ideas conveyed by Vedic testimony will also have immediate legitimacy.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; And there is no danger that anything will undermine this legitimacy, since in principle no other mode of knowledge acquisition (no other &lt;em&gt;pramāna&lt;/em&gt;, in the Sanskrit terminology) provides knowledge of &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:14&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:14&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given its role in Kumārila’s defense of Vedic authority, the doctrine of &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmāya&lt;/em&gt; has understandably incurred suspicion. But, as John Taber has pointed out, the thesis doesn’t in its own right entail the authoritativeness of the Veda.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:15&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:15&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; That requires accepting the Vedas’ authorlessness, which demands a good deal of theorizing about language and the ontology of reference, the nature of the other &lt;em&gt;pramānas&lt;/em&gt;, and so on; this is also Kumārila’s own understanding of the dialectical situation. So one could accept the Mīmāmsā school’s most general epistemological theses while rejecting Vedic authority. And I believe Taber is also right in arguing that, whatever its provenance, the &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; thesis has merit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe, though, that a satisfactory interpretation of Kumārila’s thesis has yet to be offered. In the next section, §[interpreting], I’ll explain why some prominent interpretations are inadequate, and identify some constraints for an adequate interpretation. In S[validity] I’ll develop my own interpretation, and in §[textualinterpretation] I do the exegetical work. Now as Taber says, the &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; thesis &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be considered independently of the matter of moral knowledge. II’ll do just that in §§[validity]–[textualinterpretation]. But to appreciate the theory’s merits and motives, it is necessary to discuss Kumārila’s epistemological motives more broadly, which I’ll do in §[conception]. In particular, we can understand Kumārila as attempting to reconcile a general epistemological theory with a moral epistemology, and as espousing a conception of knowledge that answers to practical as well as theoretical considerations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interpretative-approaches-and-contraints&quot;&gt;Interpretative Approaches and Contraints&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us return to Kumārila’s thesis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CS&lt;/em&gt; 47–8. The validity of all valid cognitions is to be understood as intrinsic, since a potency not existing intrinsically cannot be brought about by something else. And [in general] things depend on [other] causes in arising, but once they exist they exercise their functions by themselves.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:16&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:16&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tells us less than we might suppose. The commentarial nature of the Indian philosophical tradition means that conspicuous novelty is avoided. As such, all of the members of a given school will defend nominally the same answer to what is nominally a single question of inter-school interest. In fact different schools, and different writers within a school, may be answering different questions.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:17&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:17&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Likewise nominally identical theses may not at all mean the same thing to different writers. The &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; thesis is a case in point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every school had a position on whether &lt;em&gt;prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; was &lt;em&gt;svatah&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;paratah&lt;/em&gt; to cognition. In English this is often glossed as a question about whether the ‘truth’ or ‘validity’ (&lt;em&gt;prāmānya&lt;/em&gt;) of a cognition is intrinsic (&lt;em&gt;svatah&lt;/em&gt;) or rather extrinsic (&lt;em&gt;paratah&lt;/em&gt;) to that cognition. A scholar will sometimes begin a survey by saying that the Nyāya school holds that truth is extrinsic to cognitions—where the Nyāya view is roughly that there is never a feature of a cognition which establishes that cognition’s accuracy—and then go on to explain how the Buddhists think that both truth &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; falsity are extrinsic to cognitions, even though that would be an absurdity on the Nyāya understanding of ‘truth.’ Buddhists can say that &lt;em&gt;prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;aprāmānya&lt;/em&gt; (‘invalidity’ or ‘falsity’) are both &lt;em&gt;paratah&lt;/em&gt; because they have a quite different understanding of &lt;em&gt;prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buddhists and Naiyāyikas are different enough that no-one is much confused about this, but Mīmāmsā is closer to Nyāya and less understood, and confusion about the meanings of theses is a real danger. That there is in fact little value in saying merely that the Mīmāmsā believe that &lt;em&gt;prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;svatah&lt;/em&gt; is brought out by the observation that there were plainly different understandings of the &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmāya&lt;/em&gt; thesis in the different branches of Mīmāmsā, and even among Kumārila’s own later followers.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:18&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:18&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Still less can the standard English gloss for the thesis—‘intrinsic validity’—be supposed to convey much about Kumārila’s position. (But this gloss for “the” Mīmāmsā thesis has a long history, and is well-represented in recent discussions of Kumārila, so it would be silly to coin a new phrase now.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:19&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:19&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless Kumārila’s reasoning in vv. 47–8 allows us to eliminate at least some possible readings of ‘validity.’ Validity, which is intrinsic, contrasts with invalidity, which is extrinsic. In the following verses, Kumārila supports these claims with a regress argument: if cognitions were not &lt;em&gt;intrinsically&lt;/em&gt; valid, they would have to derive validity from further cognitions. Those other cognitions must themselves be valid if they are to help, but then, by the hypothesized extrinsic nature of validity, there would have to be yet further cognitions validating &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;, and so on &lt;em&gt;ad infinitem.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:20&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:20&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Thus validity must be intrinsic. But while other cognitions cannot make a cognition valid, they &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; make it &lt;em&gt;invalid&lt;/em&gt;, and hence invalidity is extrinsic.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:21&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:21&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Now for Buddhist philosophers, the world is made up of fleeting particulars, and the association or categorization of these particulars which is found in thought is &lt;em&gt;ipso facto&lt;/em&gt; a falsification. The notion of ‘validity’ on the Buddhist view, then, if it is to have utility, cannot be understood in terms of a correspondence between mind and world, but will rather be made out in pragmatic terms: a cognition is valid if the expectations it generates are not later frustrated. To say that validity is &lt;em&gt;svatah&lt;/em&gt;—in some way internal to the cognition itself—rules out at least that view.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:22&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:22&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But that doesn’t narrow the options enormously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;validity-as-truth&quot;&gt;Validity as truth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A popular interpretation of Kumarila’s thesis has been this: cognitions are true unless shown otherwise.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:23&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:23&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (Alternatively, validity may only &lt;em&gt;entail&lt;/em&gt; truth.) K. K. Dixit, who adopts this interpretation, responds as one might then expect:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the difficulty with Kumārila’s argumentation is that a piece of cognition not proved to be invalid is not necessarily valid, it might be valid but it might as well be otherwise.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:24&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:24&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That would indeed seem to settle the matter. But this is an uncharitable interpretation, and is anyway at odds with the text: Kumārila several times allows that a false cognition may be valid.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:25&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:25&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;validity-as-commitment&quot;&gt;Validity as Commitment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Taber has defended another interpretation, the basic lines of which he attributes to Pārthasārathimiśra, another Mīmāmsā commentator.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:26&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:26&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; According to Taber, validity is not truth but rather as it were &lt;em&gt;commitment:&lt;/em&gt; “every cognition is accompanied by an initial sense of conviction; one is initially inclined to believe of every cognition that it is true.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:27&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:27&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But Taber rightly allows that Kumārila is concerned not only with psychology but also with what is &lt;em&gt;reasonable&lt;/em&gt;. Verse 60 tells us that when a cognition is not undermined, then “there is no reasonable ground for doubt.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:28&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:28&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; So we are supposed to be &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; in accepting our beliefs as a guide to how things actually are. Taber incorporates this point into his interpretation as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One continues to be so inclined as long as the cognition is not called into question. Almost certainly, however, if the cognition is never overturned, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; true. Falsehood cannot conceal itself forever. If, over the long run, the cognition is not shown to be false, then on the basis of its initial, intrinsic validity one is certainly &lt;em&gt;justified&lt;/em&gt; in believing that it is not false, that it is really true.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:29&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:29&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, for Taber, shows Kumārila adopting a kind of hard-headed empiricism: one may believe only that for which one has evidence; but, in addition, to have &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; evidence for something (to have no evidence that your view is wrong, for example) is to be warranted in thinking that no such evidence exists.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:30&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:30&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; To ask for more is in any case futile, since the demand only leads to regress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taber’s is one of the most sympathetic and careful interpretations of Kumārila on intrinsic validity, and there is much to like about it. But how can we take seriously the idea that a cognition never undermined is “almost certainly” true, a view that Taber says is “common sense”? Dixit’s comment is again apt: it might be true and then again it might not. Suppose, for instance, that, from a distance, I mistake for a woman a man whom I am unlikely to encounter again, and would not recognize if I did. The passage of time is unlikely to expose my error. This will often be a problem in practical life as well: it is often hard to know whether one has acted well. I could not possibly have a general expectation that advice—to buy fair-trade coffee, say—will, if bad, always, or almost always, ultimately be recognized as such. Taber himself actually raises roughly the same worry about Kumrila’s defense of the Vedas, namely that they seem to come out unscathed only by default.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:31&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:31&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But he seems to think that the worry is largely &lt;em&gt;restricted&lt;/em&gt; to the Vedic case, which, as my examples show, is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difficulty here is particularly acute for Taber because, although in vv. 47–8 Kumārila says that the validity of &lt;em&gt;valid&lt;/em&gt; cognitions is intrinsic, Taber’s view that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; cognitions are intrinsically valid, at least initially. This creates the impression that &lt;em&gt;every judgement&lt;/em&gt; has &lt;em&gt;prima facie&lt;/em&gt; justification or warrant. There is no good reason, on this view, why just any judgment should not be warranted, even if it’s formed on the basis of a dream or wishful thinking. Taber may say that Kumārila’s defense of the Vedas is unsuccessful because it makes Vedic injunctions valid just by default, but really that’s tantamount to an objection to the &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; thesis itself, on Taber’s interpretation thereof. The whole &lt;em&gt;point&lt;/em&gt; would be to make cognitions justified by default, despite the fact that many types and instances of judgements—including quite empirical judgements—cannot be supposed likely to be corrected if faulty.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:32&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:32&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taber’s interpretation draws attention to crucial but often overlooked features of Kumārila’s epistemology, including the lack of coincidence between truth and validity and the importance of warrant or justification. But Taber does not explain how warrant enters the picture; the interpretation falls into the same trap that Pārthasārathi’s does, and which other scholars have noted in that context: the theory reduces to a theory of judgement.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:33&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:33&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Taber has provided an argument for his claim that a cognition “compels our assent”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:34&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:34&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; only if that means merely that judgment &lt;em&gt;entails&lt;/em&gt; assent. We are offered no reason to suppose that it would be unreasonable to stop believing something upon realizing that one does in fact believe it, if one cannot then adduce some evidence for it. But Kumārila explicitly draws the conclusion that this &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; unreasonable.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:35&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:35&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;35&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, while Taber is right to say that the &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmāya&lt;/em&gt; thesis is separable from the doctrine of Vedic authority, the thesis is plainly motivated in great part by a desire to defend the possibility of Vedic (or ‘moral’ or ‘practical’) knowledge. Even if there are independent arguments—from the threat of regress, most obviously—it does not seem to me that we do Kumārila’s view much of a service if the realm of knowledge of most interest to him fares particularly poorly on his own epistemological theory.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:36&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:36&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;36&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Besides which, it is hard to imagine that Kumārila would rest his thesis on the idea that the passage of time makes a judgement more likely to be correct when this line of thought so clearly could not, &lt;em&gt;in principle&lt;/em&gt;, apply to the Vedic case, and which, indeed, would make validity &lt;em&gt;extrinsic&lt;/em&gt; in an obvious sense, since it would accrue with time. But Taber’s interpretation relies on this claim, for which the textual evidence is ambiguous at best.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:37&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:37&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;37&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two further points, besides those to which Taber draws attention, will help in constructing a better interpretation. The first stems from a bit of a puzzle. As noted, it seems that, on Taber’s interpretation, any judgement or belief whatever is supposed to be possessed of validity. He insists that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; cognitions are valid, unless sublated or otherwise brought into doubt by some further cognition—at which point they are not really cognitions anymore at all, because they have been abandoned psychologically. And that is a common reading of Kumārila. But the Mīmāmsās, like other schools, provide a list of the sources of knowledge or valid cognition—for the Mīmāmsās the list includes, among other things, perception, inference, and testimony.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:38&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:38&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;38&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But what would be the need for such a list if every cognition is automatically valid?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact Kumārila does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; think that every cognition is valid—mere fancies or wishful thoughts, for example, are not valid.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:39&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:39&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Kumārila also notably excludes memorial judgements from the realm of validity—only cognitions or judgments with novel contents are apt for validity.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:40&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:40&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; And although memories are, on Kumārila’s view, generally recognizable as such, it isn’t &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; obvious whether a judgment is memorial, since on the &lt;em&gt;Mīmāsā&lt;/em&gt; view mistaken judgements—formed, say, in a dream—&lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; effectively memorial events or collocations of memorial elements. So we cannot say that every judgement has intrinsic validity, or that any commitment we have is warranted barring some counter-indication. In which case we’ll need to find a way to understand how cognitions can be &lt;em&gt;intrinsically&lt;/em&gt; valid without severing the connection between &lt;em&gt;valid sources of cognitions&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;valid cognitions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second point is this. The Mīmāmsās are strict about distinguishing the mental state which provides some awareness of the world (I will call this a first-order cognition) from the mental state which provides awareness of that first-order cognition (I’ll call this a second-order cognition).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:41&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:41&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;41&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Some Indian schools are in accord with Descartes: a cognition is itself present to consciousness as it reveals its object. Not so Mīmāmsā.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:42&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:42&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But the implications of this point for the &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; thesis have not been properly appreciated. In effect, we have &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; theses.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:43&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:43&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;43&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One thesis concerns the status of the first-order cognition, and the second concerns the apprehension of that status by a second-order cognition. It may then be, for example, that only some cognitions &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; valid, but that every cognition, when apprehended, is &lt;em&gt;taken to be&lt;/em&gt; valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view the failure to appreciate this second point is partly responsible for the failure to appreciate the first. Tara Chatterjea, for example, though observing that the &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmāya&lt;/em&gt; thesis is really two theses, says that Kumārila makes “contradictory suggestions” concerning the scope of the &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmāya&lt;/em&gt; thesis, and identifies v. 53 as apparently claiming that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; cognitions are intrinsically valid, in contrast with e.g. v.47 which says only that &lt;em&gt;valid&lt;/em&gt; cognitions are intrinsically valid.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:44&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:44&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;44&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (Taber also relies on v. 53 in claiming that all cognitions are valid.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:45&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:45&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;45&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) But if v. 47 concerns the status of a cognition while v. 53 concerns the &lt;em&gt;assessement of&lt;/em&gt; the status of a cognition, then that is too quick. We may thus hope that care regarding these two points will make an adequate interpretation possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-new-interpretation-of-kumrilas-intrinsic-validity&quot;&gt;A New Interpretation of Kumārila’s Intrinsic Validity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the &lt;em&gt;Codanāsūtra&lt;/em&gt; is dense and difficult, I begin by describing my interpretation of Kumārila’s &lt;em&gt;svatah&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;prāmāya&lt;/em&gt; thesis in general terms. Then, interpretation in hand, I’ll take up exegesis in §[textualinterpretation].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Validity’ has, for Kumārila, as for most Indian philosophers, both a causal (or psychological) aspect and also a normative aspect; in India, as in the West, different understandings of perception were taken to have implications for what we can know, and epistemological commitments motivated views about mind and perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginning with the psychological side, consider the idea, common in the history of philosophy, that experience confronts us with certain &lt;em&gt;appearances&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;ideas&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;impressions&lt;/em&gt; (though these appearances need not always be pictorial or visual in nature). One may hope that these appearances at least sometimes resemble or represent the world in some way. Locke, for example, thought that they sometimes did, and that we could sometimes be confident of this; the Stoics had a comparable view. Certain ancient skeptics thought that indeed our impressions &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; resemble or represent the world, but they argued that we can never know whether—and should not believe that—they do. Hume and Kant, in different ways, decided that the whole question was nonsense. Parallel positions existed in India concerning what we have called ‘cognitions.’ As in the early modern case, skepticism was more threat than reality, but Locke, Hume and Kant have their counterparts among Naiyāyikas, Buddhists, and idealists. And, as a start, we can think of Indian cognitions as being roughly equivalent to the West’s appearances or impressions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might think of cognitions or appearances as offering themselves for either acceptance or rejection. This is the view of some of Kumārila’s opponents—hence an objection considered by Kumārila to the effect that cognitions do not present themselves as authoritative.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:46&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:46&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;46&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For Kumārila himself, on the other hand, a cognition does not simply present the cognizer with a view or thought which he might, but equally well might not, accept as his own. For Kumārila, to form a cognition is, as Taber says, already to view the world in the way portrayed by the cognition.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:47&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:47&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;47&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Kumārila’s case, the language of ‘appearance’ may in fact easily mislead. Taber employs such language too uncritically when he sees in Kumārila “a kind of rigid philosophical realism which insists strictly on the reality of appearances,” and when he says that the “emphasis on the inability to distinguish true from false cognitions expresses what seems an almost skeptical attitude on the part of Kumārila, viz., that we can never establish with absolute certainty that a cognition corresponds with reality.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:48&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:48&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;48&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This suggests that we stand back from, or in judgment of, cognitions, which Kumāriladoes not think is the normal case. It’s not so much that skeptical questions can’t be settled as that they don’t arise, precisely because, for Kumārila—and this much is uncontroversial—our cognitions just constitute the way we see things without any prior need for the passing of evidential judgments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider on the one hand a (representational) painting. One may appreciate it without supposing that what is represented there ever existed elsewhere. For most of us, on the other hand, a photograph or recording invites us to suppose that we are getting a bit of a glimpse of another time and place. Only when something seems off about the photograph do we feel the need to inspect it more carefully—when what is displayed seems very improbable, say, or when a face on the cover of a magazine is suspiciously free of wrinkles. But Kumārila’s cognitions are not like paintings &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; photographs. A photograph, like a painting, is something which stands apart from own way of seeing things, and Kumārila does not believe cognitions are like that. A better analogy for Kumārila’s cognitions would be a (very clean) window. One may realize that there is a window at the end of a hall because one has already seen through it to the trees beyond. If one realizes that there is a window, that is only because one has already looked through it. Likwise, the existence of a cognition is inferred from what is shown us by it, once we have already adopted it as part of our thinking.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:49&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:49&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;49&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was noted earlier that the ‘intrinsic validity’ thesis is really &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; theses, one about a first-order cognition and one about a second-order cognition. There are likewise two aspects of the thesis still considered as a psychological thesis, and we are now in a position to articulate these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ψα: Cognitions are transparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ψβ: The existence of a cognition is inferred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, as regards the first-order cognition, the claim (Ψα) is that it is the nature of cognitions to provide a window on the world, rather than a picture of it—to have a cognition just is, at least in the basic case, to have a view of the world. Regarding the second-order case, the point (Ψβ) is that one reads the existence of the first-order cognition off of the portion of the world thus revealed (you see the trees through the window, and because you can see trees you may infer that there is a window). The first-order cognition does not become an object of thought directly; it can be contemplated, indirectly as it were, without stepping back from the cognition or regarding it as something now in question, or as something which might now be rejected, since it is the very having of the view that makes it possible to recognize the cognition.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:50&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:50&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;50&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kumārila also claims that &lt;em&gt;invalidity&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;extrinsic&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;parata&lt;/em&gt;). If cognitions manifest the world rather than representing it, Kumārila nevertheless thinks that cognitions may err in various ways. We might again compare a window, which, even if clean and without impurities—so that we cannot inspect it directly—may yet be warped or tinted so that although we see the world through it and not in it, we see the world through it &lt;em&gt;wrongly&lt;/em&gt;. The thesis that invalidity is extrinsic emphasizes the point that even when a cognition portrays the world wrongly, we cannot consider it directly and note features of that cognition that are misleading, the way you could point out parts of a photo that may mislead. What you can do is form new cognitions, which may reveal that earlier cognitions were defective. Kumārila identifies two cases. First there is the case where you directly apprehend something as being different than you had thought: this is like looking out of a different window, seeing that it’s bright outside, and realizing that the first window had been tinted. Second there is the case where you realize that the first cognition was formed in some defective way: this is like being told that the windows are tinted and realizing that it must then be brighter out than you thought.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:51&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:51&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;51&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extrinsic invalidity thesis, regarded as a psychological thesis, may thus again be divided into two parts, corresponding to the first- and second-order cases respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ψα-: Cognitions do not contain signs of their own defeciencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ψβ-: One can only appreciate the deficiencies of a cognition through a further cognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thesis is that there is nothing in a cognition itself which could indicate a problem with it—a problem can only be indicated by another cognition, or by something turned up by another cognition (either because it reveals the world differently or because it reveals that the first cognition was formed in a problematic way). And second, for the very same reason, one can only &lt;em&gt;recognize&lt;/em&gt; a problem with a cognition on the basis of what is turned up by some further cognition. The difference between the two cases is that, in the first case, one might never even notice that one had possessed a cognition that was problematic: one might adopt a new view without ever noticing an evolution in one’s thinking, or one might wind up holding inconsistent views (i.e. one might retain the original view). In the second case, by contrast, the original cognition is &lt;em&gt;seen&lt;/em&gt; to be defective. To see the old cognition as defective (as invalid) is already to have set it aside, and the new cognition which revealed the defectiveness of the first has thus become your new way of seeing the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kumārila sometimes appeals to the fact that a cognition is present and manifesting the world in a certain way as a reason for saying that cognitions are intrinsically valid.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:52&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:52&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;52&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But Kumārila also says that even invalid cognitions can manifest the world, at least until the error is noticed.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:53&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:53&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;53&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This point seems to have been overlooked (i.e. by interpreters who think that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; cognitions are—at least initially—valid) primarily on account of a failure to distinguish the first- and second-order cases.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:54&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:54&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;54&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Kumārila also assumes that once an error has been acknowledged, the erroneous cognition is set aside; thus a cognition will manifest the world in a certain way until it is recognized to be invalid. Thus again it has been supposed that validity and manifestation go hand in hand. But again this conflates the first- and second-order theses. A cognition could continue to manifest the world a certain way even after its invalidity has been revealed, if that invalidity has not been noticed (in the same way that you can learn something new without realizing that it undermines something else you believe). And there is another way that manifestation may come apart from validity. It is only cognitions derived from certain sources that can be valid: in particular valid cognitions derive from valid modes of knowledge. But you could see the world some way without having a view that is even apt for validity. (Memorial beliefs, for example, are not validity-apt.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:55&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:55&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;55&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) A cognition is intrinsically valid, then, neither in virtue of being accurate nor in virtue of manifesting (or pretending to manifest) the world. A cognition is intrinsically valid when it constitutes a genuine (though perhaps distorted) window on the world, in virtue of having a psychological or causal basis which allows it to be such a window. Cognitions arising from another source, however much they present or seem to present the world, and however accurately they do so, are not and cannot be valid, intrinsically or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Kumārila generally describes cognitions and validity in psychological or causal terms, he takes his account to have (what we would consider to be) normative implications, and we can consider Kumārila’s thesis to have a normative or evaluative aspect.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:56&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:56&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;56&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the normative side, we may understand validity as the status a cognition has when one is rationally entitled to it: I’ll call it ‘warrant’ or ‘entitlement.’ Once again there are two theses here, corresponding to the first- and second-order cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Φα: A cognition’s warrant does not depend on other cognitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Φβ: Seeing a cognition as warranted does not require seeing it as supported by other cognitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first-order case, the claim (Φα) is that the warrant of a cognition does not depend on its being buttressed by further cognitions. (Thus, for example, if you read in the &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; that Hirut is beautiful, and come to believe that Hirut is beautiful, this belief does not require, for its warrant, that you have any other supporting belief—that the &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; is a reliable source, say.) Second (Φβ), one may realize that one possesses no evidence (or no further supporting beliefs) for some belief without being rationally required to suspend or abandon that belief. Indeed, barring undermining evidence, it is irrational to reject your beliefs. (So, for example, suppose you realize that you believe Hirut is beautiful, but can’t remember how it is that you came by that belief. If you’re reasonable, and barring some more definite source of doubt, you will stand by this belief regardless.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say that invalidity is extrinsic again means two things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Φα-: a warranted cognition loses that warrant when some further cognition undermines it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for example, the belief that Hirut is beautiful will lose its warrant if you read that the reporter has been fabricating stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Φβ-: A cognition is properly judged unwarranted when it is seen to be undermined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you realize that the reporter discovered to have been fabricating stories is the reporter who wrote about the beautiful Hirut, then you will properly see the belief you had about the beautiful Hirut as unwarranted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cognition is not simply warranted by default. The warrant of a &lt;em&gt;warranted&lt;/em&gt; cognition is intrinsic in the sense described. But to have that status in the first place depends on the causal or psychological origin of the cognition. Hence the list of ‘valid’ &lt;em&gt;sources&lt;/em&gt; of cognition, or of warrant-grounding sources of cognition. Thus a cognition arrived at through testimony, inference, perception, or other sound basis of knowledge is warranted—though it may not be &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt;, since not every belief derived from perception (say) is in fact veridical. A cognition originating merely in a dream or wishful thinking was never even warranted in the first place, though it may very well masquerade as a valid cognition, and as a cognition from a good source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are the psychological and the normative aspects of &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; related? In Kumārila’s view, the various &lt;em&gt;pramānas&lt;/em&gt; are ways of opening up windows (in the form of cognitions) on the world. They don’t represent it but rather reveal it. This is what distinguishes the &lt;em&gt;pramānas&lt;/em&gt; from other sources of cognition such as wishful thinking or dreams—and even, in Kumārila’s view, from memory, which is parasitic on genuine &lt;em&gt;pramānas&lt;/em&gt;. And if this is how &lt;em&gt;pramānas&lt;/em&gt; work, it would be a mistake to distance yourself from your cognitions, as if they merely represented the world, or as if in looking around your surroundings you were only looking at something in your own head. A confused philosophical perspective on these matters leads to skepticism—it did so, or was thought to, in India as in the West—and a clear view ought to ward off that skepticism. Now of course sometimes we’re wrong about things—Kumārila doesn’t pretend otherwise. One often learns this in the ordinary course of things, as when one gets a closer view or a view in better light. But it is because cognitions open up the world to us the way they do that we can correct ourselves in that manner.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:57&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:57&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;57&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kumārila’s claim that cognitions are grasped as valid—the second-order intrinsic validity thesis—may give the impression that Kumārila is trying to help himself to evidence. But we can now see that grasping a cognition as being valid corresponds more closely to &lt;em&gt;reasonably believing something in a self-aware and occurrent manner&lt;/em&gt; than it does to &lt;em&gt;believing that a belief is reasonable.&lt;/em&gt; The latter—believing that a belief is reasonable—looks like it ought generally to be a response to some kind of evidence one can marshall regarding the belief in question (or its content). But that kind of reflective attention involved in &lt;em&gt;evaluating&lt;/em&gt; a belief is different from the reflective attention involved in simply &lt;em&gt;exploring&lt;/em&gt; one’s beliefs. Consider the familiar idea that, in order to figure out what one believes, one looks not inward but rather &lt;em&gt;outward&lt;/em&gt; towards the world—or the world as one sees it. Suppose I’ve seen Hirut, and I’m asked at some later point whether she is beautiful (or whether I believe that she is). I’ll think back to what she looked like, or try to frame her image in my mind, and then say “yes” or “no” depending on what I see there. There need be no question in this case of assessing evidence in any ordinary sense. I’m not going to review the visual conditions in which I first saw her, or anything like that. This is the case Kumārila is concerned with (and which he thinks is the normal case). And Kumārila’s claim then seems fair. This kind of reflection just assumes the reasonableness of the original belief, and it’s hard to see how else it could be. In Kumārila’s view there is no need to be concerned with the further question about the basis of one’s beliefs, so far as no particular cause for concern arises; indeed, if there were such cause for concern, you could never answer this simple question about whether Hirut is beautiful: the moment you thought back on Hirut your earlier cognition of her would have to be in doubt. Compare J. L. Austin on demanding how one knows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you say ‘That’s not enough’, then you must have in mind some more or less definite lack. ‘To be a goldfinch, besides having a red head it must also have the characteristic eye-markings’: or ‘How do you know it isn’t a woodpecker? Woodpeckers have red heads too’. If there is no definite lack, which you are at least prepared to specify on being pressed, then it’s silly (outrageous) just to go on saying ‘That’s not enough’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:58&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:58&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;58&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That also helps us to make sense of the idea that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; cognitions may be taken as valid just in virtue of being cognitions. Sure enough, not every cognition &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; valid. But accepting it as valid doesn’t &lt;em&gt;make&lt;/em&gt; it valid, either: Kumārila does not think that reflection renders a cognition valid any more than it renders cognition invalid, and neither does taking a cognition to be valid in any way establish that it is valid, or even imply that any evidence favors that cognition (unless such evidence as is manifested in that cognition already). It does not mean that warrant or evidence has &lt;em&gt;accrued&lt;/em&gt;. To put the point differently, we might say that Kumārila is interested rather in &lt;em&gt;being&lt;/em&gt; justified than in &lt;em&gt;having&lt;/em&gt; a justification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, Kumārila’s view is that reasonable belief does not &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; inquiry into evidence; it is no part of his view that there is anything &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; with such inquiry. We saw above that Taber attributed to Kumārila the idea that if no contrary evidence comes up then there must not be any. But whether or not that is Kumārila’s view, it is not part of the present doctrine. There is thus no willful blindness in this approach, though the Mīmāmsās’ larger aim of defending Vedic authority may create that impression. Kumārila’s view is not that testimony (for instance) ought always to be accepted unquestioningly. There are lots of reasons why one might distrust any given testimony, and likewise for other cognition-forming mechanisms. It is only that Kumārila gives no ground to skepticism. The fact is that quite often we know or can easily know plenty about the various ways we form our beliefs and about when further investigation is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exegesis&quot;&gt;Exegesis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted, the &lt;em&gt;CS&lt;/em&gt; is a commentary on &lt;em&gt;MS&lt;/em&gt; I.i.2, which says that “duty is a purpose having injunction for its sole authority.” A number of the initial verses of the &lt;em&gt;CS&lt;/em&gt; are concerned with minor clarifications of that thesis, but vv. 5–6 are close to a statement of the chapter’s main theses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;5. Inasmuch as authoritative character [regarding duty] is possible only to the Word, [Śābara] has also pointed out the incapacity, with regard to such objects [necessary for knowledge of duty], of Sense-Perception and the rest, which is to be described hereafter.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;6. Even with regard to purely non-existing objects, the Word brings about some conception. And consequently, in the absence of any discrepancy, authoritative character must be accepted to belong to it by its very nature.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:59&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:59&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;59&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The later parts of the &lt;em&gt;CS&lt;/em&gt; are concerned more with the role and value of testimony as opposed to the other sources of knowledge alluded to here in v. 5, and the earlier portions (up to around v. 102) focus on the general epistemological theses (of interest to us) indicated in v. 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latter verse picks up on a common Mīmāmsā theme, namely the independence of testimony as a source of knowledge:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:60&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:60&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; testimony produces cognitions, including of things non-existent, hence which could not have been produced by sense perception or any other &lt;em&gt;pramāna&lt;/em&gt;—and thus is a &lt;em&gt;primitive&lt;/em&gt; producer of cognitions, i.e. a &lt;em&gt;pramāna&lt;/em&gt; in its own right. Now this seems rather problematic. On the one hand Kumārila will not want to count just anything as a &lt;em&gt;pramāna&lt;/em&gt; merely because it leads us to think things. But if the point is rather (as I think it is) that testimony can (at least in the case of Vedic testimony regarding duty) provide us with a window on things that other &lt;em&gt;pramānas&lt;/em&gt; cannot, then the claim will be question-begging. But this is only a preliminary statement of the view (and fortunately we are not concerned with the case of testimony specifically), so we may simply note that a primitive cognition-producing mechanism is &lt;em&gt;eo ipso&lt;/em&gt; a producer of &lt;em&gt;valid&lt;/em&gt; cognitions. The starting-point for the discussion of &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; is an objection to the Mīmāmsās doctrine that an authorless text is our authority on &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;, the nub of which objection Kumārila presents himself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;22. It is always an object perceived by other means of knowledge that is got at by the Word [testimony]; and, like memory, no authority can belong to it by itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one accepts testimony, it is because “it is an assertion of a person who is believed to have perceived the object.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:61&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:61&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;61&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In other words, testimony is not a primitive source of knowledge like perception or inference are. The objector adds that we sometimes disregard testimony when we &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; judge the source reliable—and how could that be, if a reliable source isn’t in fact essential to testimony as a source of knowledge?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:62&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:62&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The opponent also makes the objection I worried about a moment ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;25. “Thus then, as even when producing a conception, Fancy, &amp;amp;c., are no authorities by themselves, so we may apply the same rule to the case of Veda also.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, again, we do not want to say that just any psychological mechanism which produces some judgment is therefore to be accorded authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kumārila responds by broadening the inquiry, turning away from the specific case of testimony:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;33. With regard to all conceptions, you must consider the following question: “Is the authoritativeness or unauthoritativeness due to itself or to something else?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three possible positions besides Kumārila’s own:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;34. Because those that are by themselves false cannot by any means be proved to be true. Some people attribute both (authoritativeness and its contrary) to (the conception) itself. Others attribute them to the proved excellences or discrepancies of its origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first sentence Kumārila briefly hints at his reason for rejecting the view which will prove to be the principle rival to its own, namely that invalidity is intrinsic and validity extrinsic (he will return to it at v. 38ff, and we return to it on p.  below). The remaining possibilities are, first, that both validity and invalidity might be intrinsic to cognitions, and, second, that both might be extrinsic to cognitions. Verses 35–7 are devoted to rejecting these two possibilities. Regarding the first, Kumārila says that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;35. Both cannot be due to itself, because the two are mutually contradictory&lt;em&gt;$\ldotp\ldotp\ldotp\ldotp$ &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;36. How can it be possible that any one thing, independent of all extraneous agency, should have contradictory characters? …&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;37. If “non-contradictoriness” were possible with regard to different conceptions—even then, if nothing else is taken into consideration, it cannot be ascertained which is which, and where.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We might, uncharitably, see the argument of vv. 35–6 as turning on a confusion of type and token—after all, why shouldn’t some cognitions have the one character and other cognitions the other? Verse 37 would then acknowledge the confusion and offer a better argument. But that would be an unhelpful procedure, and v. 36 offers some textual basis for rejecting this reading. Verse 36 asks not just how cognitions could have contradictory characters, but specifically how anything could have contradictory characters &lt;em&gt;independently of all extraneous agency.&lt;/em&gt; If we were talking about a single cognition it would not matter whether or not extraneous agencies were implicated—a single thing could not be valid and invalid at the same time regardless. That suggests that even in vv. 35–6 Kumārila has in mind cognitions in general rather than particular cognitions—some cognitions will be valid and some invalid, but the difference has to be explained by further, external factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why should we have to appeal to extraneous factors to explain the difference? And what then is the real objection in vv. 35–6 to the possibility that both validity and invalidity might be intrinsic? A reasonable possibility is that Kumārila thinks that either validity or invalidity should be in some sense &lt;em&gt;natural&lt;/em&gt; to conceptions. But then only one or the other could be natural to cognitions in general, not both. Thus if validity were natural or intrinsic to cognitions then the invalidity of a given cognition would require some further explanation appealing to extrinsic factors. This interpretation would fit the language employed in the string of objections that are shortly posed. Thus 38: “for those that hold the authoritativeness of conceptions to be natural…”; v. 40: “if authoritativeness were inherent or natural…”; v. 44: “while unauthoritativeness, being natural….” So it seems reasonable to say, on the basis of vv. 35–6, that, for Kumārila, the question of the intrinsic or extrinsic nature of validity or invalidity is a question about the natural state of cognitions in general, the point then being that there could be (at most) only one such natural state. Remember that part of what of what Kumārila is considering is whether cognitions are presentative or rather &lt;em&gt;re&lt;/em&gt;presentative;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:63&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:63&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;63&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; here Kumārila is saying that at any rate they aren’t &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In v. 37 Kumārila sets aside the inquiry into cognitions in general. Now he considers the possibility that cognitions should be considered individually. Might some then be intrinsically valid and others invalid, just as there are both natural redheads and natural blondes? Kumārila now objects that “it cannot be ascertained which is which, and where.” The idea, I think, is this. The suggestion at hand is that some cognitions are presentative by nature and others representative.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:64&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:64&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;64&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But in Kumārila’s view, there remains an open question about the accuracy of a representation which does not arise in the case of a presentation. So the suggestion being considered in v. 37 is effectively a suggestion that sometimes cognitions arrive warranted, as it were, while other times cognitions are warranted only when supported or certified by another cognition. The “which is which and where” objection seems very much to the point: Kumārila’s thought would be that the suggestion just mooted undermines the possibility of intrinsic validity altogether—for how could you be warranted in accepting the intrinsically warranted cognitions if you can’t tell them apart from the ones that need to be certified by appeal to another cognition? A cognition that requires either buttressing or discarding must be discarded if you can’t buttress it; but if you can’t tell the cognitions to which that requirement applies apart from the cognitions to which it doesn’t, how can you be rationally required to stand by the latter, given that for all you know they must either be buttressed or discounted? True, there could still &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; intrinsically warranted beliefs—i.e. cognitions to which you are entitled even if they are not supported by other cognitions. But that entitlement would seem to disappear upon reflection.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:65&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:65&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;65&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Much of the epistemological benefit of understanding cognitions as presentative would thus disappear if it is only in the nature of &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; cognitions or types of cognitions to be presentative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the latter halves of vv. 35–6, Kumārila argues that validity and invalidity cannot both be &lt;em&gt;extrinsic&lt;/em&gt; to cognitions either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;35. … Nor can both be due to something else, because in this latter case, there would be no definiteness in the conception.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;36. … And when devoid of both these characters, of what form could the conception be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here Kumārila restricts his attention to individual cognitions, so if ‘being devoid of both characters’ would mean that a cognition is neither presentative nor representative, neither warranted nor unwarranted, then it’s unsurprising that Kumārila would dismiss this possibility. This seems to be confirmed when we look at what Kumārila means by saying that these cognitions would lack ‘form’ or ‘definiteness.’ Consider v. 168, which comes in the course of a discussion of sentence meaning and the importance of reliable speakers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;168. Though the meaning [of a sentence] may have been comprehended beforehand, yet it depends for its definiteness upon the fact of its originating directly from the [trustworthy] speaker’s cognition; hence such a fact can only be comprehensible through the comprehension of the meaning. But in the matter of authenticity, it takes the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to say that while &lt;em&gt;understanding&lt;/em&gt; a sentence is simply a matter of sentence meaning, definiteness and authenticity (ie. validity) are a matter of the source of the belief in question. In any case the “definiteness” of a cognition seems to depend somehow on the causal origin of that cognition. What would that mean? It seems plausible to suppose that Kumārila is gesturing at the difference between merely entertaining a thought and having a thought that is delivered by some belief-producing mechanism which lends it weight (the latter corresponding to Kumārila’s cognition-producing mechanisms).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:66&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:66&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;66&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For example, no one considering my hypothetical example of the beautiful Hirut is going to see something to actually believe in that—the example doesn’t assert that some Hirut is a beauty. But if one &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; that some Hirut is beautiful, the text would effectively present Hirut to you as beautiful. In the latter case the thought would be “definite.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considered from the perspective of warrant, the proposal in v. 168 may be urged against the idea that a cognition is warranted only if you can buttress it with some other cognition and that a cognition is also unwarranted only if it is undermined by some other cognition. For suppose that were true. Now you are reading a newspaper, and you read that a certain Hirut is beautiful. And suppose you have no particular reason for doubting this or for distrusting the newspaper. But you can only rationally adopt the belief that Hirut is beautiful if you can ground it in some other cognition. But also you can only reject it if you can oppose it with some other cognition. But then in what sense could this report be offering itself to you for acceptance, if you could accept it only by checking somewhere else for support first, but at the same time can’t rationally reject it either? Of course we could say that the newspaper is just offering you some things for consideration, but this would be exactly Kumārila’s point: you may as well have spent your morning daydreaming, if that’s all reading the newspaper gets you.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:67&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:67&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;67&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; [rival] The big question is whether validity is intrinsic and invalidity extrinsic, as Kumārila thinks, or the other way round. Verses 38–46 set out the position of Kumārila’s opponent, and some of the opponent’ reasons for saying that invalidity is intrinsic and validity extrinsic. One objection to Kumārila’s view is offered in v. 40:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;40. “If authoritativeness were inherent or natural and its absence artificial, then dream-cognitions would be authoritative, self-supported; for what is there to refute this?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is nearly a restatement of the objection of v. 25 within the new dialectical context: attention has shifted from modes of knowledge to cognitions. (There Kumārila had claimed that testimony—and thus Vedic testimony—is a source of knowledge since it produces cognitions, and the opponent had objected that cognitions are also produced by plainly problematic mechanisms.) Certainly from the perspective of warrant, the opponent’s view is intuitive: the thought is that, given all the defective ways cognitions can be formed, one can be warranted in thinking something only if one can recognize that one came by that thought in some sound way. My confidence in what I think should be affected, for example, by whether I read it in the &lt;em&gt;National Enquirer&lt;/em&gt; or on Wikipedia or in the &lt;em&gt;New York Review of Books&lt;/em&gt;, and that requires that I should have some appreciation of how my views originated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Kumārila’s response is also intuitive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;49–51. If even on the birth of conception, the object thereof be not comprehended until the purity of its cause has been ascertained by other means, then in all cases we should have to wait for the production of another conception from a new source; for until its purity has been ascertained, the conception would be equal to nothing. And this second conception too, would be true only on the ascertainment of the purity of its cause; and so on and on, there would be no limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opponent thinks that the soundness of your view should turn on your appreciation of the soundness of the origins of your view—but to this sort of verification there is no end, for how can you trust that you have indeed properly assessed the origins of your original view? Your assessment itself might be wrong, and indeed according the opponent the assessment itself should be in doubt until verified. At that rate we will never be entitled to any beliefs.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:68&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:68&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;68&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though warrant is important here, Kumārila is more directly making a psychological point, as is especially evident from the two preceding verses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;47. You must understand that authoritativeness is inherent in all Means of Right Notion. For a faculty, by itself non-existing, cannot possibly be brought into existence by any other agency;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;48. since it is only for the sake of its birth that a positive entity requires a cause. And when it has once been born, it’s application to its various effects proceeds naturally out of itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A valid cognition must of course have some causal basis, but once produced it provides comprehension of its object—that is what I take the reference to ‘faculty’ and ‘application’ to mean. Kumārila thinks that if the validity of a cognition—that, say, Hirut is beautiful—depends on some other cognition, then we would not after all have a comprehension of Hirut being beautiful until the further cognition were available. I understand the point here as follows. Suppose you pick up a copy of the &lt;em&gt;New York Times.&lt;/em&gt; In it you read a story about Ethiopia. The story is about a singer named Hirut and it reports that she is beautiful. Now suppose you know essentially nothing about the &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt;, but also have no particular reason to doubt it or to doubt its reliability in this area. (Compare asking someone on the street for the time.) And in fact you come to believe, as a result of reading the story, that there is a beautiful Ethiopian singer named Hirut. Then assuming that the reporter is an honest and careful one, with sound aesthetic sensibilities, hasn’t the &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; opened up a bit of the world for you? Doesn’t your new belief constitute a window on a little part of Ethiopia? This is what Kumārila claims is the case: a valid cognition is a window on the world, and nothing more than what has been described is required to open up that window.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:69&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:69&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;69&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does Kumārila say that once it has originated, the cognition thereby acts in this way (as this window), and that nothing could make it act this way if it couldn’t do so of it’s own accord? If we considered the matter in terms of &lt;em&gt;thoughts&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;beliefs&lt;/em&gt;, this would seem to be a mistake. Suppose another man reads the story about Hirut, but only in a detached fashion, forming no beliefs, because he dismisses the &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; as a part of the reactionary old-media elite. The report that Hirut is beautiful opens no windows for him. But then he reads that the reporter in question supports some bold progressive cause—open borders, perhaps—and thus decides the reporter must be a trustworthy sort after all. He now remembers how this reporter said that a certain Hirut was beautiful, and now believes it. Doesn’t the initial thought about Hirut now serve as a window for him, though one opened by further thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we must remember that Kumarila’s cognitions are not beliefs as we understand them. A cognition is anchored to its genetic origin—to the particular episode of perceiving or of receiving testimony that gave rise to the cognition—in a way that a belief is not. Or again, validity, unlike justification, cannot be provided later for a cognition that lacked it. A cognition either captures a view of the world or it doesn’t, and if it doesn’t then nothing can change that later. You could later come by a new cognition that gives you what the first one might have, but that will just be a different cognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if the validity of a cognition depends on other cognitions, then we’ll have a regress, while Kumārila’s view avoids that difficulty:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;52. In case, however, authoritativeness be accepted to be due to (the conception) itself, nothing else is wanted (for its cognition). Because in the absence of any cognition of discrepancies, falsity (unauthoritativeness) becomes precluded by itself (i.e. without the help of any extraneous Means).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:70&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:70&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;70&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note that Jhā—rightly—glosses ‘falsity’ here as ‘unauthoritativeness’—i.e. as invalidity. We return to ‘falsity’ in connection with v. 54 below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verse 47 above said that validity is intrinsic to all &lt;em&gt;valid&lt;/em&gt; cognitions. But v. 53 has been cited by Taber to support the reading according to which &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; cognitions are intrinsically valid, and this pair of verses has also been adduced by Tara Chatterjea to show that Kumārila’s work contains “contradictory suggestions” concerning the scope of the &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; thesis.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:71&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:71&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;71&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Therefore the authoritative character of a conception, cognised through the mere fact of its having the character of “cognition,” can be set aside only by the contrary nature of its object, or by the recognition of discrepancies in its cause.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while the discussion (both mine and Kumārila’s) has thus far primarily concerned the first-order cognition, verses 52–3 connect up the first- and second-order elements of the intrinsic validity thesis. We remember that, for Kumārila, a cognition is not itself an object &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; consciousness, though it manifests some other object &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; consciousness. If you are aware of a cognition as opposed to its object, that is because this cognition has itself become the object of a &lt;em&gt;further&lt;/em&gt; cognition. The &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; thesis in this connection concerns the relationship between cognizing a cognition and cognizing that cognition as being (i.e. cognizing it as though it were) valid.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:72&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:72&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;72&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Verse 53 is asserting that the two are the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are cognitions apprehended as valid? Because to reflect upon a cognition just is to reflect upon the world which that cognition reveals. Such reflection presupposes that the initial cognition constitutes your view of the world. For suppose instead that, upon recognizing and attending to the belief that Hirut is beautiful, you were not to apprehend it as valid—whether actually as invalid or somehow as neither valid nor invalid. Then that very second-order cognition would undermine the first-order cognition. Even granting that the initial cognition were valid up to that point, there would now be a new cognition to the effect that the first cognition is invalid or false or doubtful or whatever the case may be. Of course this new cognition might itself be invalid, but that will not always be so, even when it is false. So reflection will be a way of undermining your cognitions, except to the extent that you are able to identify some support for them. But, thinks Kumārila, reflection should not undermine our beliefs in that way. So the two forms of the &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt; thesis mesh nicely, and both are supported by the appeal to the threat of infinite regress. In v. 54 Kumarila identifies several varieties of invalidity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;54. Unauthoritativeness is three-fold: as being due to falsity, non-perception, and doubt. From among these, two (falsity and doubt) being positive entities, are brought about by discrepancies in the cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the reference to ‘positive entities,’ Kumārila responds to ontological qualms of a pan-Indian variety concerning explanation; that need not detain us.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:73&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:73&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;73&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The reference to ‘discrepancies’ is more important for our purposes: the proponent of intrinsic invalidity will claim that a cognition is rendered valid when the mechanisms which produced it are seen to have been sound, whereas Kumārila claims that a cognition is shown invalid when the mechanism is shown to have been defective, i.e. to have had ‘discrepancies.’ In v. 54 Kumārila is thus cataloguing the ways in which a cognition can be rendered invalid and saying that two of these ways are indeed reducible to the the identification of discrepancies.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:74&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:74&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;74&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (The third, non-perception, will be a special case.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By ‘falsity,’ Kumarila means not the actual falsity or inaccuracy of the initial cognition; rather he is addressing the case in which some such inaccuracy is turned up, or in which some defect in the mechanism behind the cognition is turned up, so that the initial cognition is altogether overturned. The case of doubt requires not so much an overturning as an unsettling; thus in a stock Indian example you might be unsure whether you’re looking at (or saw) a piece of silver or rather a bit of shell. Kumārila is considering these two cases in vv. 57–61:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;57. Unauthoritativeness (falsity) is got at directly through the “Cognition (of its contradictory).” For, so long as the former is not set aside, the subsequent cognition (of its contradictory) cannot be produced.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;58. Though the cognition of the discrepancy of the cause is known to refer to a different object (&lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;, not the object which is the effect of tlie cause), yet we have co-objectivity (of the two cognitions) as being implied thereby; and hence we have the preclusion of the former,—as in the case of the “milking-pot.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:75&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:75&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;75&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;59. But this rule applies only to those cases in which (with regard to the second conception) there is neither cognition of any discrepancy, nor any contradictory conception. In those cases, however, in which we have any of these two factors, the second conception becoming false, the first comes to be true.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;60. But in that case too, the authoritativeness is due to the conception itself, in the absence of any cognition of discrepancies. And in a case where there is no such cognition of discrepancies, there is no reasonable ground for doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;61. Thus (in this manner) we do not stand in need of postulating more than three or four conceptions. And it is for this reason that we hold to the doctrine of “Self-evidence” [i.e. &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘falsity’ case well illustrates one form of the extrinsic nature of invalidity. It is in having the new cognition that the earlier one is set aside and rendered invalid. And should the new cognition itself prove faulty, the original cognition is valid again not because it has gained new support but because the objections have been lifted—thus the validity of a valid cognition is intrinsic even if it loses and regains that status.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:76&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:76&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;76&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just a psychological point. It may be that, as a psychological matter, it’s impossible to credit both the old idea that Hirut is beautiful and the new idea that she’s plain, but as a psychological matter one could reject the new information rather than the old. But, for Kumarila, the new cognition is itself intrinsically valid, barring some further problem with &lt;em&gt;it&lt;/em&gt;. The process of discarding the old way of looking at things is, moreover, an inferential process and not merely a causal one. This is clearest in the case where a cognition is not just straightforwardly at odds with the earlier cognition in terms of its content, but where the new cognition reveals something problematic about the causal basis of the original cognition, which is the case Kumarila considers in v. 58. For an example, imagine that rather than seeing Hirut and finding her plain, you learn that the &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; reporter in question has abnormal aesthetic sensibilities. And notice, finally, that v. 60 above is explicit that there is a question of rationality here: it would be a &lt;em&gt;mistake&lt;/em&gt; to give up your view of Hirut’s beauty barring some specific reason for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When in the case of ‘falsity’ a cognition is set aside, it is, in a sense, not really even apt for validity any more, since it no longer constitutes one’s view of the world anyway. Likewise with the case of doubt; the view has been suspended in a way that would make it inappropriate to ask, for example, whether the subject is justified in holding it.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:77&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:77&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;77&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The same point holds doubly for the case of non-perception, the case in which you were simply not in contact with the world at all, as might be the case in dreams, or the aforementioned case of ‘fancy,’ or wishful thinking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In the case of non-perception, however, we do not admit the action of such discrepancies. Because for us all non-perception is due to the &lt;em&gt;absence&lt;/em&gt; of cause,—just as you have asserted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This case is important because it illustrates a claim I’ve made a couple of times, namely that cognition must have a certain causal origin if it was ever to have validity in the first place. ‘Fancy’ and wishful thinking, for example, are not sources of valid cognition,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:78&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:78&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;78&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but only special cases of non-perception. We remember that v. 48 had said that it was only for its birth that a positive entity required a cause—here there is no (sound) cause in the first place, and no positive entity (i.e. no valid cognition). This implicitly offers a response to the dream objection of v. 40.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The non-perception case also allows us to appreciate more clearly that validity cannot be anything like &lt;em&gt;truth.&lt;/em&gt; If I daydream the beautiful Hirut into existence, and later forget it was a daydream and come actually to believe that there was a beautiful Ethiopian singer named Hirut, the belief may or may not in fact be &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt;; Ethiopia has its singers, Hirut is a reasonably common name there, and it is a land of beautiful women; some woman may very well be all of these things. But there is no question or possibility of &lt;em&gt;validity&lt;/em&gt; here. Validity requires a causal basis (such as testimony or perception) that can (though may not always) mediate some kind of contact between you and the word. If there’s no actual chain between the world and your thoughts about it, you can’t have valid cognitions about it. Kumārila applies his conclusions to the case of testimony:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;64. In (truthful) human (speech) we find two (factors)—&lt;em&gt;absence of discrepancies,&lt;/em&gt; and (&lt;em&gt;presence of&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;em&gt;excellence&lt;/em&gt;; and we have already explained that authoritativeness cannot be due to &lt;em&gt;excellence&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;65–6. Therefore excellences must be held to help only in the removal of discrepancies; and from the absence of these latter (discrepancies), proceeds the absence of the two kinds of unauthoritativeness; and thus the fact of (authoritativeness) being inherent in Words remains untouched. And inasmuch as the word gives rise to a conception, its authoritativeness is secured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Kumārila says it has already been explained that validity cannot be due to the excellences of testimony, he must mean that a cognition is not valid in virtue of &lt;em&gt;recognizing&lt;/em&gt; that the source of knowledge—in this case testimony—was free of fault. He exploits this point to respond to the objection that his own view does face a regress despite his earlier protestations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“If the absence of discrepancies be held to result from excellences, then there is the same &lt;em&gt;regressus ad infinitum&lt;/em&gt; (that you urged against us.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;67. (Not so): because at that time (ie. at the time of the conception of the absence of discrepancies), we do not admit of any active functioning of the excellences, though they continue to be recognised all the same;—because in the conception of the absence of discrepancies they help by their mere presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have seen before, one need not actually have an appreciation of the soundness of the basis of a conception for it to be valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a slight puzzle here, though, because v. 67 seems to suggest that in fact a valid cognition &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; have a &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; basis—i.e. a source without discrepancies. But that cannot be right, because it would mean that testimonial cognitions are not after all valid just as such, and, as we can see even here (from the the last sentence of vv. 65–6), validity &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; depend on the actual faultlessness of the testimony in question: testimony just as such &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a source of valid cognitions. I therefore take v. 67 to mean that the &lt;em&gt;presumed&lt;/em&gt; excellences of the source of a cognition suffice (so far as the source is of an approved variety: testimony, perception, etc.). This is further confirmed by the next verses, as we turn to the case of the Vedas, where Kumārila claims that the very testimonial nature of Vedic-derived cognitions imbues them with validity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;70. Hence the mere fact of the Veda not having been composed by an authoritative author, ceases to be a discrepancy&lt;em&gt;$\ldotp\ldotp\ldotp\ldotp$ &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;71. It is only human speech that depends for its authority upon another Mean of Right Knowlede; and hence in the absence of the latter, the former becomes faulty; but the other (ie. Vedic sentences) can never be so (on that ground).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have returned here to the second-order case: testimonial cognitions may be presumed sound just on the basis of being testimonial cognitions, though in the typical or human case, where testimonial knowledge is parasitic on other sources of knowledge, that presumption would be overruled by the observation that the testifier had no way of coming by his supposed knowledge. In the case of the Vedas, no such difficulty can arrive, and the presumption stands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verse 72 returns us to the matter of independence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Thus then, the very fact of the incompatibility of the Veda with other Means of Right Notion, constitutes its authoritativeness; for if it were not so incompatible, it would only be subsidiary (to other such means).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point here is that since Vedic testimony produces cognitions which could never be called into question by any other source of knowledge, the Vedas are an authority: they produce cognitions which must be trusted. This may seem to reopen our question about dreams and fancies. Perhaps you have dreams about the future, and come to have beliefs about the future in that way, and these beliefs cannot be undermined by perception or inference. Does that make dreaming authoritative concerning the future? Kumārila does not think so, but not, I think, for deep reasons of epistemological theory proper. It is just that dreaming and Vedic testimony are different cases. On Kumārila’s view, dreams and fancies just take the matter of perception and mix it up in arbitrary ways; they are not new sources of information. One could, of course, say the same about the Vedas—but then you wouldn’t be a &lt;em&gt;Mīmāmsāka&lt;/em&gt;. Kumārila thinks that language and meaning are deep and primitive aspects of the cosmos, that the cosmos is eternal, that it’s reasonable to suppose that the Vedas were never written, and that they tap into eternal meanings somehow. Those are matters separate from epistemology, nor does Kumārila suppose himself to have defended any of those claims at this stage.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:79&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:79&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;79&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We pass over vv. 73–81, which continue discussing the independence of Vedas, and arrive at an objection in v. 82:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;82. (Objection): “But Sense-Perception and the rest are not comprehended as that ‘these are authoritative’; nor is it possible to carry on any business by means of such perceptions, when they are not comprehended as such.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opponent objects that since in forming cognitions we do not yet have any confidence in those cognitions, they cannot be a basis for action or further inference. In responding, Kumārila provides a helpful recapitulation of his view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;(Reply): Even prior to comprehension, the Means of Right Notion had an independent existence of their own and they come to be comprehended subsequently (as such), through other cognitions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cognition is valid and serves as a basis for action and inference even without any recognition of its existence; when its existence is recognized, this is in a new cognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;84. Therefore the fact of its being comprehended as such, does not in any way help the authoritativeness (of the Means of Right Notion); because the idea of the object is got at through the former alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second-order recognition of a cognition as valid is not necessary for the validity of that first-prder cognition, nor can it confer validity upon it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Even the unauthoritative Means would, by itself, lead to the conception of its object; and its function would not cease unless its falsity were ascertained by other means.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even an invalid cognition manifests the world, though it may do so wrongly (it may for example ‘reveal’ a real shell to be a piece of silver&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:80&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:80&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;80&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;), but until it is revealed as misleading it is accepted, and forms a basis for further inference. Notice here that a cognition can be invalid but still manifest the world. We should also see here a connection to action: so far as v. 85 itself goes, we might think that the ‘function’ of a cognitions was restricted to manifestation, and that may indeed be the primary meaning, but in the context of the objection of the objection at v. 82, Kumārila evidently means that, in virtue of the exercising its function, a cognition (even an invalid one) functions as a basis for action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally we end with a reiteration of the intrinsicality of validity and the extrinsicality of invalidity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;86. The falsity of an object is not, like its truthfulness, perceived by its very first conception. For the recognition of unauthoritativeness, the only cause is one’s consciousness of the falsity of its subject itself, or of he faultiness of the cause thereof.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;87. Thereby alone is falsity (of a conception) established; and by no other means. And the truthfulness (or authoritativeness of a conception) is proved to &lt;em&gt;belong to the state of its birth&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;, is natural or inherent in it).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;88. Therefore even in cases where falsity is proved by other means, these two (causes of falsity) should be noted, and not only certain points of similarity (with another false idea).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have clarified a number of puzzles about the text that remained in other interpretations, and found confirmation for the approach I laid out in the previous section. We have reaped these rewards primarily by simply attending carefully to the difference between the first- and second-order aspects of the &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmāya&lt;/em&gt; thesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kumrilas-conception-of-knowledge&quot;&gt;Kumārila’s Conception of Knowledge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we wish to sympathize with Kumārila’s theory rather than only to set it out, it will be helpful to conclude by looking briefly at a couple of historical comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For analogies with Kumārila’s intrinsically valid cognitions, Taber adduces Descartes’ “clear and distinct ideas,” the truth of which are self-evident, and, again, the Stoic’s notion of a ‘&lt;em&gt;φαντασία καταληπτική&lt;/em&gt;,’ an impression or appearance which contains some mark guaranteeing its own truth or accuracy.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:81&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:81&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;81&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Taber grants that, in contrast with &lt;em&gt;kataleptic&lt;/em&gt; impressions or clear and distinct ideas, intrinsically valid cognitions are common; on Taber’s interpretation all cognitions are at least initially intrinsically valid. But the more important disanalogy, which Taber must himself insist on, but nevertheless seems really to &lt;em&gt;spoil&lt;/em&gt; the analogy, is that intrinsically valid cognitions needn’t be true, whereas the whole point of the Stoic and Cartesian notions is to isolate a special class of impressions or ideas which are sure to be such. J. N. Mohanty is, I think, right in saying that the whole spirit of Kumārila’s view is to &lt;em&gt;reject&lt;/em&gt; the notion of self-evidence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it is precisely the contention of the &lt;em&gt;svatahprāmānya&lt;/em&gt; theory…that &lt;em&gt;there is no criterion of truth, though there are criteria of error.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:82&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:82&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;82&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nearer Hellenistic counterpart for Kumārila is Philo. According to what seems to be the dominant reconstruction, Philo, who led the Academy for some time, was initially a radical skeptic in the manner of Clitomachus, then later adopted the mitigated skepticism of Metrodorus, and finally in his (unfortunately not extant) ‘Roman Books’ advocated a sort of fallibilism.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:83&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:83&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;83&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Academics seem to have generally accepted (if only for the purpose of launching counter-arguments) the Stoic understanding of knowledge, which required the afore-mentioned &lt;em&gt;kataleptic&lt;/em&gt; impressions: knowledge requires an accurate impression appropriately caused by what it represents, and which contains some mark which shows that it meets those two conditions. The Academics argued that there were no such impressions, since any true impression could be mimicked by a false one. The skeptics, like the Stoics, thought that one ought not to assent to what one does not know; thus a radical skeptic would ideally refuse ever to assent to anything. A mitigated skepticism, on the other hand, would allow the reasonableness of forming some beliefs even without allowing the existence of a criterion of truth; some appearances might at least constitute good, if never conclusive, evidence. But ultimately Philo reinterpreted the notion of a &lt;em&gt;kataleptic&lt;/em&gt; impression, accepting the requirements of truth and of a suitable causal basis, but removing the requirement that such an impression guarantee its own truth, which he still considered to constitute an impossible standard. This meant that it might not only be reasonable to form beliefs but that &lt;em&gt;kataleptic&lt;/em&gt; impressions were after all possible, and one might rationally accept these without qualificaton. But since the requirement for a criterion of truth had been abandoned, one might very well be mistaken about whether one actually possessed a &lt;em&gt;kataleptic&lt;/em&gt; impression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philo’s innovation provoked a good deal of hostility. He had, in effect, given up the idea that knowledge must be certain (or infallible)—something assumed by dogmatists and skeptics alike. Kumārila’s validity does not require truth, but, like Philo, he decided that the reigning epistemic standard was impossible for any cognition to attain, and thus redefined it so that it could be claimed as a matter of course, as it properly should have been. As with Philo’s view, this view was met by complaints from outside Kumārila’s own school and with disbelief from inside it. Thus a later commentator, Umbeka, found a way interpret Kumārila as making validity entail truth after all. In India, as in the Hellenistic world, knowledge was supposed to be infallible, and Kumārila’s innovation, like Philo’s, lies precisely in giving up that requirement as in any case impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both cases, the reinterpretation of knowledge is at least in part a response to the demands of practical activity. A major criticism of the radically skeptical position was that it made action and virtue impossible, since both require belief. Efforts were made to reconcile action with the skeptics’ traditional refusal to assent, but the mitigated skeptical position amounted to a way of allowing assent without admitting the possibility of knowledge or certainty. Since the mitigated position winds up buying into dogmatic conception of knowledge in a way that radical skeptics could claim to avoid (the latter could more easily claim to ‘accept’ it only to attack it), the Philonian position can be understood as an attempt to just find a new understanding of knowledge that was a better fit with the practical considerations driving the mitigated skeptics’ concessions in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kumārila likewise reinvents the notion of knowledge to allow for the demands of practice. Moral or &lt;em&gt;dharmic&lt;/em&gt; knowledge will be impossible without the authority of Vedic texts—the Buddhists, for example, are wrong to suppose that perception will suffice. But Vedic testimony cannot meet the standards imposed by the epistemological theories of other schools, which would require either a kind of self-evidence of which no cognition is capable, or verification which is in this case impossible. How then would one pursue &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;? Human beings must act, and they must have moral guidance. It cannot be unreasonable to act as best you can, relying on the best resources available, even if the soundness of these resources cannot be established. That is part of what it is to be reasonable, and the standards of theoretical reason are misconceived if they seem to say otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abbreviations&quot;&gt;Abbreviations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CS&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Codanāsūtra&lt;/em&gt; of Kumārila (=&lt;em&gt;SV&lt;/em&gt; ch. II)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MS&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Mīmāmsā Sūtra&lt;/em&gt; of Jaiminī&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PV&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Prāmānyavāda&lt;/em&gt; of Gangeśa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SV&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ślokavārttika&lt;/em&gt; of Kumārila&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SVVT&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ślokavārttikavyākhyātātparyatīkā&lt;/em&gt; of Umbeka&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TS&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Tattvasangraha&lt;/em&gt; of Śāntaraksita (quotes Kumārila’s lost &lt;em&gt;Brhattīkā&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;jaimini1923mimamsa&quot;&gt;Lal, M. L. (1923). &lt;i&gt;The Mı̂mâmsâ sûtras of Jaiminı̄&lt;/i&gt;. Sudhindra Nath Vasu.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;keith1921karma&quot;&gt;Keith, A. B. (1921). &lt;i&gt;The Karma-Mı̄māṁsā&lt;/i&gt;. Association Press.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;tabereternality&quot;&gt;Taber, J. Mı̄māṃsā and the Eternality of Language. In M. Kapstein (Ed.), &lt;i&gt;The Columbia Guide to Classical Indian Philosophy (forthcoming)&lt;/i&gt;. Columbia University Press.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;jha1907skb&quot;&gt;Jhā, G. (1907). &lt;i&gt;C̣lokavārttika&lt;/i&gt;. Asiatic Society of Bengal.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;pollock1989mima&quot;&gt;Pollock, S. (1989). Mı̄māṃsā and the Problem of History in Traditional India. &lt;i&gt;Journal of the American Oriental Society&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;109&lt;/i&gt;(4), 603–610.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;matilal1986perception&quot;&gt;Matilal, B. K. (1986). &lt;i&gt;Perception: An Essay on Classical Indian Theories of Knowledge&lt;/i&gt;. Oxford University Press, USA.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;arnold2001ivr&quot;&gt;Arnold, D. (2001). Intrinsic Validity Reconsidered: A Sympathetic Study of the Mimamsaka Inversion of Buddhist Epistemology. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Indian Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;29&lt;/i&gt;(5–6), 589–675.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;taber1992dkb&quot;&gt;Taber, J. (1992). What did Kumārila Bhaṭṭha Mean by \emphSvataḥ Prāmāṇya? &lt;i&gt;Journal of the American Oriental Society&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;112&lt;/i&gt;(2), 204–221.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;mohanty1989gangesa&quot;&gt;Mohanty, J. N. (1989). &lt;i&gt;Gaṅgeśa’s Theory of Truth&lt;/i&gt;. Motilal Banarsidass.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;chatterjea2003svatah&quot;&gt;Chatterjea, T. (2003). \emphSvataḥ-Prāmāṇyavādah in \emphMı̄māṃsā. In &lt;i&gt;Knowledge and Freedom in Indian Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;. Lexington Books.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;radhakrishnan1927indian&quot;&gt;Radhakrishnan, S. (1927). &lt;i&gt;Indian Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;. Macmillan.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;potter1984die&quot;&gt;Potter, K. H. (1984). Does Indian Epistemology Concern Justified True Belief? &lt;i&gt;Journal of Indian Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;12&lt;/i&gt;(4), 307–327.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;potter1992presuppositions&quot;&gt;Potter, K. H. (1992). &lt;i&gt;Presuppositions of India’s Philosophies&lt;/i&gt;. Motilal Banarsidass.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;mohanty1984pramanya&quot;&gt;Mohanty, J. N. (1984). Prāmāṇya and Workability—Response to Potter. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Indian Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;12&lt;/i&gt;(4), 329–338.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;bhatt1962epistemology&quot;&gt;Bhatt, G. P. (1962). &lt;i&gt;Epistemology of the Bhāṭṭa school of Pūrva Mı̄mānsā&lt;/i&gt;. Chowkhamba Sanskrit Series Office.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;dixit1983slokavarttika&quot;&gt;Dixit, K. K. (1983). &lt;i&gt;Ślokavārttika: A Study&lt;/i&gt;. L.D. Institute of Indology, Ahmedabad.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hiriyanna1932outlines&quot;&gt;Hiriyanna, M. (1932). &lt;i&gt;Outlines of Indian Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;. Routledge.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;taber1987review&quot;&gt;Taber, J. (1987). Review of Dixit. &lt;i&gt;Journal of the American Oriental Society&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;107&lt;/i&gt;(1), 103–104.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;taber2002mo&quot;&gt;Taber, J. (2002). Mohanty on Śabdapramāṇa. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Indian Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;30&lt;/i&gt;, 161–190.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;taber2005hindu&quot;&gt;Taber, J. A. (2005). &lt;i&gt;A Hindu Critique of Buddhist Epistemology: Kumārila on Perception&lt;/i&gt;. Routledge.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;arnold2001ivs&quot;&gt;Arnold, D. (2001). Of Intrinsic Validity: A Study on the Relevance of Purva Mimamsa. &lt;i&gt;Philosophy East and West&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;51&lt;/i&gt;(1), 26–53.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;dasgupta1957history&quot;&gt;Dasgupta, S. (1957). &lt;i&gt;A History of Indian Philosophy&lt;/i&gt; (Vol. 1, p. 323). Cambridge University Press.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;sen1984concept&quot;&gt;Sen, D. (1984). &lt;i&gt;The Concept of Knowledge: Indian Theories&lt;/i&gt;. K P Bagchi.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kataoka2002validity&quot;&gt;Kataoka, K. (2002). Validity of Cognition and Authority of Scripture. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Indian and Buddhist Studies&lt;/i&gt;, 1022–1026.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;austin1979other&quot;&gt;Austin, J. L. Other Minds. In &lt;i&gt;Philosophical Papers, 3rd ed.&lt;/i&gt; Oxford University Press.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;alston1980level&quot;&gt;Alston, W. P. (1980). Level-Confusions in Epistemology. &lt;i&gt;Midwest Studies in Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;5&lt;/i&gt;(1), 135–150.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kripke1972naming&quot;&gt;Kripke, S. A. (1972). Naming and Necessity. Harvard University Press.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;frede1987sceptic&quot;&gt;Frede, M. (1987). The Sceptic’s Two Kinds of Assent. &lt;i&gt;Essays in Ancient Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;barnes1989antiochus&quot;&gt;Barnes, J. (1989). Antiochus of Ascalon. &lt;i&gt;Philosophia Togata&lt;/i&gt;, 51–96.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;striker1997academics&quot;&gt;Striker, G. (1997). Academics Fighting Academics. &lt;i&gt;Assent and Argument&lt;/i&gt;, 257–76.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;brittain2001philo&quot;&gt;Brittain, C. (2001). &lt;i&gt;Philo of Larissa: the Last of the Academic Sceptics&lt;/i&gt;. Oxford University Press.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;sep-philo-larissa&quot;&gt;Brittain, C. (2008). Philo of Larissa. In E. N. Zalta (Ed.), &lt;i&gt;The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/i&gt; (Fall 2008.). \urlhttp://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2008/entries/philo-larissa/.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Trans. &lt;a href=&quot;#jaimini1923mimamsa&quot;&gt;Lal (1923)&lt;/a&gt;. For style, clarity, or to remove or add glosses, I’ve lightly altered most of the older translations I’ve quoted. Meaning has not (I hope) been affected. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For a survey of the school see e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;#keith1921karma&quot;&gt;Keith (1921)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Credited with the &lt;em&gt;Brahma&lt;/em&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;Vedānta&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;em&gt;Sūtras&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śābarabhāsya&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;ad loc.&lt;/em&gt; Though he notes that Mīmāmsākas must still rule out other potential ways of knowing &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;, for example by inference or analogy. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The restriction to matters invisible was taken seriously by Mīmāmsā: what the Vedas said about anything other than &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; was reinterpreted or disregarded.[invisiblenote] &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I leave aside the part about the eternal connection between words and meanings, which would take us too far afield. Suffice it to say that the Mīmāmsākas spilt a good deal of ink developing an ontology and a philosophy of language to make room for the idea of testimony that is authoritative but authorless. See &lt;a href=&quot;#tabereternality&quot;&gt;Taber&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Trans. &lt;a href=&quot;#jha1907skb&quot;&gt;Jhā (1907)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Thus &lt;a href=&quot;#pollock1989mima&quot;&gt;Pollock (1989, p. 606)&lt;/a&gt;, who argues that Mīmāmsā itself encouraged the rejection of history. But there was already fertile soil, e.g. in the cyclical conception of the universe. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tabereternality&quot;&gt;Taber&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#matilal1986perception&quot;&gt;Matilal (1986, p. 32)&lt;/a&gt;; see &lt;a href=&quot;#arnold2001ivr&quot;&gt;Arnold (2001, pp. 589–91)&lt;/a&gt; on the modern reception of the doctrine of &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Testimony (&lt;em&gt;śabda&lt;/em&gt;) is sometimes treated under the heading of ‘injunction’ (&lt;em&gt;codanā&lt;/em&gt;) because the Mīmāmsā school is concerned with Vedic testimony insofar as it offers prescriptions for living, whether in a grammatical form or not (see also n. [invisiblenote] above). In our passages, Kumārila is explicitly treating &lt;em&gt;śabda&lt;/em&gt; in general (vv. 7–8). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Trans. &lt;a href=&quot;#taber1992dkb&quot;&gt;Taber (1992, p. 207)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Thus v. 68: “Then, too, in the case of the Veda, the assertion of &lt;em&gt;freedom from reproach&lt;/em&gt; is very easy to put forward, because there is no speaker in this case; and for this reason the unauthoritativeness of the Veda can never even be imagined.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:14&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;vv. 13–8. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:14&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:15&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#taber1992dkb&quot;&gt;Taber (1992)&lt;/a&gt; [p. X]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:15&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:16&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;vv. 47–8; cf. e.g. vv. 6, 80. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:16&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:17&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cf. &lt;a href=&quot;#mohanty1989gangesa&quot;&gt;Mohanty (1989, p. 1)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:17&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:18&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;So for example Prabhākara before Kumārila, and Umbeka, Pārthasārathi, and Sucarita after him—see &lt;a href=&quot;#chatterjea2003svatah&quot;&gt;Chatterjea (2003)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#taber1992dkb&quot;&gt;Taber (1992)&lt;/a&gt; for brief accounts. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:18&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:19&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The usage goes back at least to &lt;a href=&quot;#keith1921karma&quot;&gt;Keith (1921)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#radhakrishnan1927indian&quot;&gt;Radhakrishnan (1927)&lt;/a&gt;, and is employed in the recent discussions of Kumārila offered by &lt;a href=&quot;#taber1992dkb&quot;&gt;Taber (1992)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#arnold2001ivr&quot;&gt;Arnold (2001)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:19&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:20&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;E.g. vv. 49–51. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:20&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:21&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;E.g. vv. 52–3, 56, 86–7. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:21&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:22&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Even with Kumārila it’s not trivial to rule out a pragmatic understanding. Karl &lt;a href=&quot;#potter1984die&quot;&gt;Potter (1984)&lt;/a&gt; [&lt;a href=&quot;#potter1992presuppositions&quot;&gt;Potter (1992)&lt;/a&gt;] has argued that ‘knowledge’ has &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; more a pragmatic than a theoretical import in Indian philosophy—but see &lt;a href=&quot;#mohanty1984pramanya&quot;&gt;Mohanty (1984)&lt;/a&gt;. A pragmatic understanding of validity was read into the &lt;em&gt;SV&lt;/em&gt; itself by Sucarita Miśra, a later Mīmāmsā commentator—see &lt;a href=&quot;#chatterjea2003svatah&quot;&gt;Chatterjea (2003, pp. 52–3)&lt;/a&gt;. My own interpretation gives a role to pragmatic considerations; cf. also &lt;a href=&quot;#bhatt1962epistemology&quot;&gt;Bhatt (1962)&lt;/a&gt; [pp. XX]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:22&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:23&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Assuming a correspondence understanding of truth. But scholars of Indian philosophy also often use ‘truth’ as a label of convenience, and thus may describe Kumārila’s thesis in these terms without subscribing to the interpretation now under consideration. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:23&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:24&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#dixit1983slokavarttika&quot;&gt;Dixit (1983, p. 5)&lt;/a&gt;; for validity as truth see also e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;#chatterjea2003svatah&quot;&gt;Chatterjea (2003)&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;#hiriyanna1932outlines&quot;&gt;Hiriyanna (1932)&lt;/a&gt;; among traditional authors see e.g. Gangeśa, &lt;em&gt;PV&lt;/em&gt; [XX]. &lt;a href=&quot;#bhatt1962epistemology&quot;&gt;Bhatt (1962)&lt;/a&gt; interprets validity as truth-entailing, but understands intrinsicality in a way that would avoid Dixit’s complaint; classically, cf. Umbeka &lt;em&gt;SVVT&lt;/em&gt; [XX]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:24&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:25&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Thus &lt;em&gt;CS&lt;/em&gt; v. 6 (trans. Jhā): “Even the unauthoritative Means would, by itself, lead to the conception of its object, and its function could not cease unless its falsity were ascertained by other means.” Cf. e.g. vv. 85–6. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:25&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:26&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#taber1992dkb&quot;&gt;Taber (1992)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:26&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:27&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;p. 216; cf. &lt;a href=&quot;#taber1987review&quot;&gt;Taber (1987, p. 203)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#taber2002mo&quot;&gt;Taber (2002, p. 172)&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;#taber2005hindu&quot;&gt;Taber (2005, p. 2)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#arnold2001ivr&quot;&gt;Arnold (2001)&lt;/a&gt; [&lt;a href=&quot;#arnold2001ivs&quot;&gt;Arnold (2001)&lt;/a&gt;] is broadly supportive of the Taber-Pārthasārathi interpretation. For other suggestions in terms of presumptive or &lt;em&gt;prima facie&lt;/em&gt; truth see &lt;a href=&quot;#keith1921karma&quot;&gt;Keith (1921, p. 18)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#dasgupta1957history&quot;&gt;Dasgupta (1957, pp. 372–5)&lt;/a&gt;, who offers a coherentist spin, and &lt;a href=&quot;#bhatt1962epistemology&quot;&gt;Bhatt (1962)&lt;/a&gt; [pp. 131ff.]. &lt;a href=&quot;#chatterjea2003svatah&quot;&gt;Chatterjea (2003, p. 52)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#mohanty1989gangesa&quot;&gt;Mohanty (1989, p. 8)&lt;/a&gt; also suggest that—at least in Pārthasārathi’s case—the claim is a psychological one. On Pārthasārathi’s interpretation cf. &lt;a href=&quot;#chatterjea2003svatah&quot;&gt;Chatterjea (2003, pp. 50–5)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#bhatt1962epistemology&quot;&gt;Bhatt (1962, pp. 129–45)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:27&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:28&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cf. &lt;em&gt;TS&lt;/em&gt; 2872–4, noted by Taber. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:28&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:29&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;p. 216, his emphases. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:29&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:30&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;pp. 205, 216. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:30&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:31&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;p. 217. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:31&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:32&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Taber (p. 215, n. 56) cites v. 80 in support of the idea that the passage of time improves confidence, but while the verse shows that Kumārila is trying to make more than a psychological point, I cannot see in it any indication that he is thinking about the passage of time, except in the trivial sense that a counter-indicating cognition would come after the initial cognition. Taber also adduces &lt;em&gt;TS&lt;/em&gt; 2904, but again I see in that verse only the claim that cognitions are valid if they’re not upset by other cognitions. Kumārila refers in this verse to cognitions occurring at “other times and places,” but that doesn’t mean that length of time (or travel experience, for that matter) makes a difference to warrant except insofar as counter-indication cognitions would, by their nature, have to occur at other times.[tabertextual] &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:32&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:33&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Thus &lt;a href=&quot;#mohanty1989gangesa&quot;&gt;Mohanty (1989, p. 8)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#chatterjea2003svatah&quot;&gt;Chatterjea (2003, p. 52)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:33&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:34&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;p. 216. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:34&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:35&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;v. 60; cf. vv. [XX], &lt;em&gt;TS&lt;/em&gt; 2872–4. Taber himself acknowledges the importance of this point.[reasonableness] &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:35&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:36&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A complicating factor here is the Mīmāmsā adherence to the view (very contentious in the Indian setting) that ‘absence’ (&lt;em&gt;abhāva&lt;/em&gt;) is a sound means of acquiring knowledge. That is, one may rightly infer from the absence of any indication of something that it doesn’t exist. But this principle makes no appeal to the passage of time, and Kumārila is liberal and reasonable about what counts as an indication of a real or potential difficulty about evidence. Taber does not rely on an appeal to &lt;em&gt;abhāva&lt;/em&gt; in his defense of &lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:36&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:37&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See n. [tabertextual]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:37&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:38&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The six &lt;em&gt;pramāas&lt;/em&gt; of (Bhāa) &lt;em&gt;Mīmāsā&lt;/em&gt; are perception (&lt;em&gt;pratyaka&lt;/em&gt;), inference (&lt;em&gt;anumāna&lt;/em&gt;), comparison (&lt;em&gt;upamāna&lt;/em&gt;) testimony (&lt;em&gt;śabda&lt;/em&gt;), postulation (&lt;em&gt;arthāpatti&lt;/em&gt;), and absence (&lt;em&gt;abhāva&lt;/em&gt;).[thesix] &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:38&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:39&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;vv. 94–5; cf. also vv. 85 and 128. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:39&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:40&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SV&lt;/em&gt; II.22–3, V.11. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:40&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:41&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SV&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Śūnyavāda&lt;/em&gt; v. 64ff.; for the school see  &lt;a href=&quot;#keith1921karma&quot;&gt;Keith (1921, pp. 20–1)&lt;/a&gt; and citations there. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:41&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:42&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;#sen1984concept&quot;&gt;Sen (1984)&lt;/a&gt; [pref., chs. 4, 10] for discussion. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:42&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:43&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;cf. &lt;a href=&quot;#chatterjea2003svatah&quot;&gt;Chatterjea (2003, p. 41)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:43&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:44&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chatterjea2003svatah&quot;&gt;Chatterjea (2003, p. 51)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:44&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:45&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#taber2002mo&quot;&gt;Taber (2002)&lt;/a&gt; [p. 171, n. 27], &lt;a href=&quot;#taber1992dkb&quot;&gt;Taber (1992, p. 212)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:45&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:46&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;v. 85. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:46&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:47&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The intrinsic validity of cognitions is vested for the Mīmāmsaka in the sense of conviction with which they typically arise.” &lt;a href=&quot;#taber2002mo&quot;&gt;Taber (2002, p. 172)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:47&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:48&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#taber1992dkb&quot;&gt;Taber (1992)&lt;/a&gt;, pp. 206 &amp;amp; 215; cf. pp. 207, 216, 218, 221. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:48&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:49&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SV&lt;/em&gt; [XX]. Compare the familiar idea that, in order to figure out what one believes, one (often) looks not inward but outward, towards the world. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:49&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:50&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We must leave aside the details of Kumārila’s theory of perception, which would also take us into his metaphysics and philosophy of language, but a translation of the relevant chapter of the &lt;em&gt;SL&lt;/em&gt; (the &lt;em&gt;Pratyaksapariccheda&lt;/em&gt;), along with extensive notes and discussion, has recently been provided by &lt;a href=&quot;#taber2005hindu&quot;&gt;Taber (2005)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:50&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:51&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#kataoka2002validity&quot;&gt;Kataoka (2002)&lt;/a&gt; outlines the structure of invalidity; cf. &lt;a href=&quot;#bhatt1962epistemology&quot;&gt;Bhatt (1962, p. 132)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:51&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:52&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See e.g. vv. 6, 47, 85. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:52&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:53&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;v. 85, cf. vv. 25, 94–5. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:53&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:54&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The other factor is perhaps the failure to see the connection between the validity of means of knowledge and the validity of cognitions. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:54&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:55&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SV&lt;/em&gt; [XX]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:55&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:56&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For citations see n. [reasonableness] above. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:56&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:57&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It is particularly characteristic of the Indian tradition to (as we would see it) transform normative or evaluative questions into epistemological or metaphysical questions, so far as possible. Most notoriously, there seems to have been virtually no direct philosophical inquiry into final ends—no ethics or moral philosophy in the Western sense. The introduction has already given an illustration of the kind of thing that happened instead: debates about final ends were fought by proxy, in terms of epistemology, ontology, perception, language, and so on, with each school developing an increasingly sophisticated philosophical apparatus to buttress their approach to duty or liberation. See further &lt;a href=&quot;#sen1984concept&quot;&gt;Sen (1984)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:57&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:58&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#austin1979other&quot;&gt;Austin (p. 84)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:58&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:59&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Jhā refers to ‘cognitions’ as ‘conceptions’; ‘validity’ is ‘authoritativeness’; `intrinsic is ‘inherent’; Jhā also uses ‘means of right notion’ to refer to a valid cognition. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:59&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:60&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See §[intro] above. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:60&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:61&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;v. 23. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:61&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:62&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;v. 30. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:62&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:63&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See §[interpoutline] above. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:63&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:64&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;At least that’s how Kumārila, a realist, would look at the matter. As indicated in §[interpreting] above, other Indian philosophers would have seen the matter differently. It’s not clear that Kumārila is really trying to seriously respond to such views as opposed to just considering all of the possibilities in a realistic spirit. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:64&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:65&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;At present we are asking a question about the warrant of the first-order cognition, and not a question about how it can be &lt;em&gt;determined&lt;/em&gt; whether a first-order cognition is warranted. But one part of the suggestion in the contemplated scenario is that some cognitions may be warranted only &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; assessed in a certain way. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:65&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:66&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cf. &lt;a href=&quot;#sen1984concept&quot;&gt;Sen (1984)&lt;/a&gt; [ch. 1] and eg. &lt;em&gt;SV&lt;/em&gt; IV.v.78. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:66&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:67&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;[TESTIMONY ISSUES] &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:67&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:68&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;cf. v. 56, and &lt;a href=&quot;#alston1980level&quot;&gt;Alston (1980)&lt;/a&gt; on ‘level-confusions.’ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:68&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:69&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Compare &lt;a href=&quot;#kripke1972naming&quot;&gt;Kripke (1972, pp. 66–7)&lt;/a&gt; on Jonah. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:69&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:70&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cf. v. 56: “The fact of mere Unauthoritativeness being due to discrepancies does not lead to any &lt;em&gt;regressus ad infinitum&lt;/em&gt;—as is found to be the case with the theory of the cognition of excellences (being the cause of authoritativeness)—for us who hold the theory of “self-evidence” [&lt;em&gt;svatah prāmānya&lt;/em&gt;].” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:70&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:71&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See §2.3 above. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:71&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:72&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#mohanty1989gangesa&quot;&gt;Mohanty (1989, p. 3)&lt;/a&gt; offers a useful note on the difference between (and different positions on) grasping ‘&lt;em&gt;prakāśa&lt;/em&gt;’ and grasping ‘&lt;em&gt;prāmānya&lt;/em&gt;,’ and see &lt;a href=&quot;#sen1984concept&quot;&gt;Sen (1984)&lt;/a&gt; for a more extensive treatment. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:72&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:73&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;These were mooted by the opponent at vv. 38–9. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:73&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:74&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Notice it’s not enough for there to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; discrepancies—they must be turned up somehow. Otherwise those cognitions would not have been valid in the first place, and Kumārila is claiming that they were. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:74&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:75&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The ‘milking-pot:’ Kumārila adduces an example from ritual (Jhā &lt;em&gt;ad. loc.&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:75&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:76&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;vv. 59–60. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:76&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:77&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A doubt carries no commitment in any direction in the first place—this point fits with my earlier discussion where I supposed that validity presupposses &lt;em&gt;definiteness&lt;/em&gt; as I interpreted that term; cf. &lt;a href=&quot;#bhatt1962epistemology&quot;&gt;Bhatt (1962, pp. 93–5)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:77&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:78&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;vv. 94–5; cf. v. 128. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:78&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:79&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Verse 70 in its entirety runs thus: “Hence the mere fact of the Veda not having been composed by an authoritative author, ceases to be a discrepancy. Of the syllogistic arguments urged against us, we shall lay down counter-arguments hereafter.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:79&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:80&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Jhā &lt;em&gt;ad loc.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:80&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:81&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;p. 217. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:81&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:82&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#mohanty1989gangesa&quot;&gt;Mohanty (1989, p. 22)&lt;/a&gt;, his emphasis. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:82&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:83&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#frede1987sceptic&quot;&gt;Frede (1987)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#barnes1989antiochus&quot;&gt;Barnes (1989)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#striker1997academics&quot;&gt;Striker (1997)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#brittain2001philo&quot;&gt;Brittain (2001)&lt;/a&gt;; see &lt;a href=&quot;#sep-philo-larissa&quot;&gt;Brittain (2008)&lt;/a&gt; for a survey. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:83&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Socrates&rsquo; Conception of Knowledge</title>
   <link href="https://bhritchie.github.pages/2014/11/15/socrates-conception-of-knowledge/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://bhritchie.github.pages/2014/11/15/socrates-conception-of-knowledge</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;!---

FULLER ABSTRACT:

The notion of \emph{techne}---expertise---is prominent in Plato&#39;s earlier dialogues. \emph{Techne} has generally been of interest to scholars because of its role in Socrates&#39; (or Plato&#39;s) moral psychology. But this has led to an inadequate appreciation of Socrates&#39; own particular conception of \emph{techne}, and has obscured the extent of his engagement with epistemology proper. In this chapter I articulate the Socratic understanding of \emph{techne}, and argue that \emph{techne} in fact represents Socrates&#39; understanding of \emph{knowledge}. This conception of knowledge fuses forms of knowledge we would distinguish, including propositional knowledge and know-how, and thus takes essentially practical and goal-directed varieties of knowledge as paradigmatic of knowledge as a whole. I explain also how this motivates some points in Socrates&#39; moral psychology, including his famous denial of \emph{akrasia}: this is necessitated by his conception of moral knowledge as a \emph{techne.}

---&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;abstract-label&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/span&gt;. I articulate the Socratic understanding of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;—expertise—and argue that, for Socrates, &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; is knowledge. This sheds light on various other aspects of Socrates’ philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unscientific polling on my part has revealed that, when asked for examples of things they know, modern English speakers will always give examples in (or appropriate to) propositional form: “I know that Addis Ababa is the capital of Ethiopia,” “two plus two equals four,” “God loves me”—that sort of thing. Nobody has ever said “carpentry” or “how to play the piano,” or anything like that. That is the situation in contemporary philosophy as well, where epistemologists emphasize knowledge of particular facts; Thus Robert Audi, in a recent introduction to epistemology, can say flatly that “knowledge is constituted by belief (of a certain kind).”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t take much acquaintance with Plato’s earlier dialogues to know that Socrates &lt;em&gt;loves&lt;/em&gt; examples of the other sort—in particular, examples of practices of the skilled, often professional variety which were called “&lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Socrates’ contemporaries certainly noticed this: Callicles complains that Socrates never lets up with his “continual talk of shoemakers and cleaners, cooks and doctors”; Xenophon even records the Athenian tyrants warning Socrates that he had better lay off discussing carpenters and herdsmen and blacksmiths and the like.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern readers do not exactly miss these examples, but the &lt;em&gt;significance&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; in the early dialogues is often ill-appreciated. It is not always seen that Socrates’ scattered reflections on &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;—which constitute a very significant part of the dialogues—constitute, in fact, reflections on knowledge. Thus so great and sympathetic an interpreter as Gregory Vlastos was able to say that Socrates was “exclusively a moral philosopher.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On occasion Socratic epistemology &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; taken up in its own right, but even then &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; generally gets too little emphasis. Hugh Benson is by no means alone in saying that for Socrates, knowledge is more like &lt;em&gt;understanding&lt;/em&gt; than like the (for us) more familiar &lt;em&gt;justified true belief&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; He offers some “paradigmatic examples of the kind of understanding [he has] in mind”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We say things like Einstein understands gravity, Richard Feynmann understands quantum mechanics, R. G. Collingwood understands history, or James Boswell understands Samuel Johnson.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Callicles does not complain that Socrates never leaves off talking about cosmological theories; the tyrants do not warn Socrates that he should stop talking about historical figures or battles. To talk only of “understanding” leaves us in the dark as to why this should be. We would do better to put more emphasis on &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scholarly interest in &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; has instead mainly been due to interest in the so-called “craft analogy”—the supposed Socratic analogy between virtue and &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. But even then the &lt;em&gt;distinctiveness&lt;/em&gt; of Socrates’ conception of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; often goes unnoticed. Terence Irwin, author of perhaps the most important recent book on Plato’s moral theory, tells us that “Socrates does not say exactly what he takes to be implied by saying that something is a craft [i.e. a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;] or is similar to a craft.” He goes on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Aristotle, however, has a fairly clear and explicit view of the &amp;gt; character of a craft. It is useful, then, to replace the rather &amp;gt; imprecise question ‘Does Socrates treat virtue as a craft?’ with the &amp;gt; more precise question ‘Does Socrates treat virtue as the sort of thing &amp;gt; that Aristotle regards as a craft?’&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Socrates certainly says enough about &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; to distinguish his conception thereof from Aristotle’s, and it is a mistake to suppose that two conceptions are close enough for interpretative purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We moderns do talk about knowledge of non-propositional varieties all the time. And Socrates talks about propositional varieties of knowledge. But, generally, once we start &lt;em&gt;thinking about&lt;/em&gt; knowledge, we start thinking about knowledge in propositional form. And Socrates, when he starts to think about knowledge, thinks about &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. It is not too much to say that, for Socrates, knowledge just &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. And so in this essay I describe the Socratic conception of knowledge, and argue that it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the Socratic conception of knowledge that I’m describing. In other words, I describe the Socratic conception of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, explaining how it is different from other conceptions of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; (in §1), and I explain why that is tantamount to describing the Socratic conception of knowledge altogether (in §§2–4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;techne-in-platos-early-dialogues&quot;&gt;Techne in Plato’s Early Dialogues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As ‘&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;’ was a term of commendation, there were disputes about whether given practices deserved the title.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Socrates himself engages in such disputation: he views medicine as a genuine &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, but raises questions about the status of poetry, ‘cookery,’ and rhetoric. Nor is it only Socrates raising such questions in the early dialogues: in the &lt;em&gt;Laches&lt;/em&gt;, Nicias assumes that fighting in armour is a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, while Laches has doubts.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disagreements as to which practices were &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; were complicated, and engendered, by the fact that different people had different ideas about what a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; should be or do. For example, when you hire a craftsman, should you be able to expect that he deliver what you hire him for? That would be a natural expectation of a builder, but what about a doctor? And should a genuine &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; be theoretical, and in what way theoretical? Or might a mere body of experience also constitute a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;? Thus, to take one example, we find the author of the Hippocratic &lt;em&gt;On Ancient Medicine&lt;/em&gt; (hereafter &lt;em&gt;VM&lt;/em&gt;) arguing that medicine’s status as a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; does not depend on incorporating into it the sorts of physical theories expounded by the natural philosophers.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By attending to the debates about the nature of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; which we find in the contemporary literature, and to various remarks about &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; in the early dialogues, we can identify a distinctively Socratic (or early-Platonic) conception of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. Here in §1 I discuss three important features of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; as Socrates understands it, which together give us a good general picture, and each of which emerges in discussions about whether certain practices constitute &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; or whether certain individuals possess a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. I begin with the scope of craft knowledge, in §1.1. Within its proper domain, Socrates says that “wisdom would never err” (&lt;em&gt;Euthydemus&lt;/em&gt; 280a), so I try, in §1.2, to explain what that means. For Socrates the reliable attainment of genuine goods is in part a result of the craftsman’s rational and articulate understanding, which I discuss in §1.3. In §1.4 I deal briefly with some problems stemming from the Socratic treatment of virtue as a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-scope-of-techne&quot;&gt;The Scope of Techne&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may get at the nature of a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; by way of its subject matter. Thus Socrates asks Gorgias: “with which of the things there are is oratory concerned?”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; And a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; is systematic, so that its subject matter (or &lt;em&gt;pragma&lt;/em&gt;) has a natural integrity.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the &lt;em&gt;Laches&lt;/em&gt; the proposal that courage might be knowledge of future goods and evils is rejected on the grounds that there is no such thing as knowledge concerned with farming &lt;em&gt;in the future&lt;/em&gt; in particular, or with health or strategy &lt;em&gt;in the future.&lt;/em&gt; The topic will just be health &lt;em&gt;period&lt;/em&gt;, or strategy, or farming, or goods and evils generally (198d–199d). Similarly Ion is taken to task for the suggestion that he knows and can interpret only the works of Homer, but that as far as other poets go he “has no power to contribute anything worthwhile” (&lt;em&gt;Ion&lt;/em&gt; 532b-c). One learns, or should learn, “a subject as a whole” (532e); i.e. poetry, or sculpture, not specific poets or sculptors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates characterizes the subjects of craft knowledge in fairly intuitive terms: the odd and the even, health, houses—often it’s a product the craftsman can bring about. Socrates tells us in the &lt;em&gt;Ion&lt;/em&gt; that when he finds forms of knowledge dealing with different subjects (&lt;em&gt;pragmata&lt;/em&gt;), then he calls them different &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt;, while the same subject means the same &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; (537d–e). He illustrates the point by observing that both he and Ion know that Socrates has five fingers on a hand, and it’s by the same &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;—namely arithmetic—that they know this. But this idea about distinct subject matters shouldn’t be interpreted too strictly.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:14&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:14&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; both gymnastics and medicine concern the body, but the one provides preventative care while the other is restorative. Similarly, at &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; 451b–c we find that both &lt;em&gt;arithmetike&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;logistike&lt;/em&gt; have as subjects “even and odd”; the further difference seems to be the &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; these &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; deal with number, or the use they put it to. So we are working here with the intuitive idea that each &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; has, like a science, its own proper field, along with its own particular principles and point.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:15&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:15&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-reliability-of-techne&quot;&gt;The Reliability of Techne&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; was expected to bring about success within its proper area, and proneness to failure could call the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;-status of a given practice into question.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:16&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:16&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nevertheless some forms of failure could be thought compatible with &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. One possibility is that, whatever might ideally be accomplished through &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, any given craftsman might make mistakes, as a result, perhaps, of inexperience or lack of aptitude. Socrates allows for the possibility of this kind of failure, for example at &lt;em&gt;Euthydemus&lt;/em&gt; 279e–280a, where he contrasts wise and foolish doctors or generals. But so far that says nothing about potential limits on &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; proper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another type of failure comes out in a supposed contrast between building (&lt;em&gt;tektonike&lt;/em&gt;) and medicine, the former of which seems to have been an early paradigm of &lt;em&gt;techne.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:17&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:17&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There was a trope to the effect that when you call the builder you will get a house—and you won’t get a house otherwise. But other putative craftsman aren’t always successful. Doctors don’t always restore people to health, and, what’s more, people are sometimes restored to health without the aid of doctors. On such grounds some denied that medicine was a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; at all. The orator or sophist, too, was susceptible to such charges, especially given his sometimes extravagant claims to be able to teach virtue. Again it was observed that these teachers were not always successful (how interesting that they insist on securing payment up front!), and that their students were sometimes surpassed by the untrained.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:18&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:18&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Hippocratic &lt;em&gt;De Arte&lt;/em&gt; the response to such charges is as follows. Nature (&lt;em&gt;phusis&lt;/em&gt;) sets limits on what is possible for the medical art. For example, fire is the ultimate cauterizer available to medicine—if this cauterizer is insufficient in some cases, that is no fault of medicine. The doctor still knows what can and cannot be helped, and what to do in cases that &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; amenable to treatment. Now it is important that limitations are blamed on &lt;em&gt;phusis&lt;/em&gt; here. &lt;em&gt;Techne&lt;/em&gt; was often viewed as a way of mastering or overcoming &lt;em&gt;tuche&lt;/em&gt;—i.e. chance or luck.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:19&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:19&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; So we get a distinction between the vicissitudes of fortune, against which medicine, like any good &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, is insurance, and the inexorable workings of nature, which the doctor will understand but could not be expected to resist. (As for the fact that some people get better without a doctor, that may be credited to their doing what the doctor &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; have recommended.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:20&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:20&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) Now &lt;em&gt;De Arte&lt;/em&gt; still offers us an impressively demanding standard for &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;: Allen observes that the defender of this view “seems to envisage . . . a physician who will at no point undertake cures with less than complete confidence of success” (85).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates’ understanding of the reliability of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; seems to accord with the sort of treatment found in &lt;em&gt;De Arte&lt;/em&gt;. On the one hand, Socrates treats medicine as a paradigmatic &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, and there’s no reason to suppose that he or anyone else would have thought that a doctor could heal anyone no matter what their injuries or age or health. So Socrates could hardly have a &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; stringent view than the one found in &lt;em&gt;De Arte&lt;/em&gt;. On the other hand, his view seems to be no &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; stringent either. In the &lt;em&gt;Euthydemus&lt;/em&gt;, Socrates, adducing a variety of &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt;, deploys the notion that &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; is a guard against bad &lt;em&gt;tuche&lt;/em&gt; (279d ff.), finally going so far as to say that &lt;em&gt;sophia&lt;/em&gt; (here a synonym for &lt;em&gt;‘techne’&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; (good) &lt;em&gt;tuche&lt;/em&gt; (279d), or at any rate provides it (282a). Here Socrates, like the author of &lt;em&gt;De Arte&lt;/em&gt;, tries to push luck out of the picture altogether.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:21&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:21&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; At &lt;em&gt;Euthydemus&lt;/em&gt; 280a, ‘being lucky’ is glossed as ‘never making mistakes,’&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:22&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:22&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and at least this latter characterization of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; is found elsewhere, for example at &lt;em&gt;Protagoras&lt;/em&gt; 357d–e. It is also found in &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; I, where Thrasymachus says that craftsmen, insofar as they are craftsmen, never make mistakes (340e), and Socrates falls in line with this, too (342b). The context is the question whether a ruler will ever mistakenly issue laws which in fact turn out to be detrimental to himself, so the point seems to be that if a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; is being practiced properly &lt;em&gt;then the craftsman should always be successful&lt;/em&gt; (within the realm of possibility, presumably). So again the possibility of sheer misfortune is pushed out of the picture.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:23&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:23&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later Plato will take a more generous view. While in the &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; Socrates insists that mere experience and guessing are the marks of something &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; than &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; (462b–c, 465a, 501a), the &lt;em&gt;Philebus&lt;/em&gt; has him distinguishing a class of “less precise” &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; which rely on guesswork (&lt;em&gt;stochasmos&lt;/em&gt;) rooted in experience, which would thus be less reliable (55e–56a). A later development still, with Aristotle and other writers, was the notion of a stochastic &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; (which need not be untheoretical).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:24&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:24&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Here we would distinguish between competent application of the methods associated with a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; and actual successful outcome, or between the exercise of a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; and the aim of that &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. This would seem to offer a more appropriate model for medicine: we would no longer expect the doctor to know in every case whether or not the treatment will succeed; medicine would provide no &lt;em&gt;absolute&lt;/em&gt; guarantee against luck. But, again, these are later developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;techne-and-explanation&quot;&gt;Techne and Explanation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Socrates, &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; are reliable because they are rational. In the &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; Polus says that “it is experience that causes our times to march along the way of craft, whereas inexperience causes them to march along the way of chance,” and while we see the common contrast between &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;tuche&lt;/em&gt; here, Socrates finds this statement inadequate.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:25&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:25&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Thus he later says that when some practice “has no rational account by which it applies the things it applies, to say what they are by nature, so that it cannot say what is the explanation of each thing,” then that practice is merely a product of experience (&lt;em&gt;empeiria&lt;/em&gt;), and not a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. Socrates goes on: “I don’t call anything a craft which is unreasoning” (&lt;em&gt;alogos&lt;/em&gt;—465a). He derides Polus’ own ‘&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;’ of rhetoric, comparing it to “cookery,” which “by habit and experience . . . keeps only memory of what usually happens.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:26&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:26&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A craftsman then understands the nature of the things he is dealing with. A doctor, for example, would know “what sight itself is” (&lt;em&gt;Laches&lt;/em&gt; 189e–190a). The same expectation is strongly intimated at &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; 459c–e. It has been observed that the orator may be more persuasive concerning medicine even than a doctor, at least among the ignorant, but he “isn’t knowledgeable in the thing in which a doctor is knowledgeable” (459b). Socrates asks whether&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the orator is in the same position with respect to what’s just and &amp;gt; unjust, what’s shameful and admirable, what’s good and bad, as he is &amp;gt; about what’s healthy and about the subjects of the other crafts? &amp;gt; (459d)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The doctor, by implication, &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; know health and whatever else his &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; concerns, and a rhetorical &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; ought to be similar.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:27&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:27&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Gorgias,&lt;/em&gt; the contrast between &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;empeiria&lt;/em&gt; is treated as a contrast not just between understanding and mere experience, but as a contrast between &lt;em&gt;aiming at something good with understanding&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;aiming at mere pleasure by guesswork&lt;/em&gt; (464a–465d, 500a–b). I take the point to be that if you don’t understand the nature of your aims and of your subject matter, then you’re in no position to know what would be the “good condition” of the things you treat.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:28&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:28&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Thus you cannot aim at that good condition but only, and only by guesswork, at what will please some person at some time. We might contrast an idealized cobbler, who knows the support a foot needs and how to provide it, with a shoe designer, who is concerned with aesthetic pleasure rather than comfort or health. The cobbler’s principles are always the same; the trends are ever-changing and unpredictable.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:29&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:29&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates’ interest in &lt;em&gt;what things are&lt;/em&gt; has been described as an interest in real as opposed to nominal definitions. This is fair in the sense that Socrates expects experts to be be able to articulate their knowledge. Doctors and laymen alike &lt;em&gt;talk&lt;/em&gt; about health, and can point to examples of healthy people, or give general characterizations of health—as “good condition of the body,” for example. But the layman relies on more superficial signs, and is liable to error, while the doctor can tell healthy people apart from those who merely appear healthy (&lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; 464a–b).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:30&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:30&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The doctor’s ability to give a “real definition” of health is a reflection of this ability to distinguish appearance from reality. So to know what the qualities in question are is, in part, to be able to employ &lt;em&gt;and explain&lt;/em&gt; reliable standards of assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interest in definitions should not be construed as an interest in knowledge which may be captured by a verbal formula.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:31&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:31&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Knowledge of a given entity or quality, in the sense Socrates is concerned with, already indicates mastery of the whole rational practice that constitutes a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:32&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:32&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But because the expert can articulate his reasoning, putative experts may be interrogated. And so we have the familiar type of Socratic question: “what is courage?” or “what is piety?”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:33&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:33&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As Angela Smith points out, requests for definitions follow declarations of expertise: the requests are a &lt;em&gt;test&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:34&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:34&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; And this is only &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; Socratic test for expertise. In some cases we can just &lt;em&gt;tell&lt;/em&gt; whether a wall or a shoe, say, is a good one. So one way of telling a craftsman is by his work; another is by his pedigree, or his students.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:35&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:35&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;35&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In several dialogues we see Socrates trying to elicit a suitable delineation of the scope of some supposed &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:36&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:36&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;36&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But the influential notion that Socrates is primarily interested in deductive knowledge, or knowledge of definitions, seems to be a result of taking one of Socrates’ investigative tools as too much representative of his whole conception of knowledge.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:37&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:37&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;37&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;techne-and-virtue&quot;&gt;Techne and Virtue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said that much of the scholarly interest in &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; has circled around Socrates’ frequent comparisons of virtue with various &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt;. Socrates makes these comparisons because he thinks that virtue is knowledge, and that knowledge is &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:38&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:38&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;38&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However this is a matter of much controversy, because many scholars think that &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; have features unsuitable to virtue.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:39&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:39&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Which leads to a problem for my central thesis, since if you think that virtue cannot be a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, you will probably still think that virtue is knowledge (that being an important Socratic thesis), so that it would be easy to think (mistakenly) that &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; is just one form of knowledge among others for Socrates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a seemingly attractive line of thought supports the idea that Socrates would be interested in the craft analogy even if he doesn’t himself think that virtue is a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;: a lot of people were running around Greece claiming to teach virtue—claiming, in fact, a moral &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. Socrates was showing how wrong this was. Perhaps he thought that the example of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; could be used to illuminate the nature of virtue to some extent, but it was a typically sophistic rather than Socratic idea that you could really posses a full-blown moral &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. But that line of thought becomes less attractive once we realize how Socartes’ conception of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; differs from that of his interlocutors. He never shows that Gorgias or Polus lack a moral &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; as &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; understand that notion; in fact Socrates insists that they have the &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; understanding of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. This is a rather frivolous exercise unless Socrates thinks that virtue really &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;ought to be,&lt;/em&gt; a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:40&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:40&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And perhaps attention to the distinctive features of Socratic &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; could also show us how to get out of the difficulty about unappealing features of &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt;. Here is an illustration of how that might go. One worry is that if virtue is a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, then virtue will be of only instrumental value, and Socrates surely does not think &lt;em&gt;that.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:41&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:41&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;41&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Now I don’t think it’s clear that Socrates thinks &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; are of only instrumental value.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:42&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:42&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But even if we suppose that he does, one aspect of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; suggests that an exception might be made for the case of virtue. What I have in mind is &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;’s mastery of luck (§1.2). If a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; overcomes luck within a given domain, then one might aspire to a master-&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; which overcomes luck altogether—the sort of thing Socrates describes as being or superseding luck in the &lt;em&gt;Euthydemus&lt;/em&gt; (279d ff.). And once you have the notion of such a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, it’s a short leap to the notion of a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; which is intrinsically rather than instrumentally good, since good luck (or fortune) may itself be thought of as a or indeed &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; intrinsic good: Socrates says everyone considers good fortune the greatest good (&lt;em&gt;Euthydemus&lt;/em&gt; 279c), and Aristotle says that good fortune (&lt;em&gt;eutuche&lt;/em&gt;) is or is near to well-being (&lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;—&lt;em&gt;Physics&lt;/em&gt; 197b3–4).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:43&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:43&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;43&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates recognizes the difficulties his model of knowledge presents for an understanding of virtue. But that does not mean he rejects that model of knowledge—after all, he has no other. It’s interesting rather to see how that model can be adapted in different ways or how other aspects of Socrates’ thought are suited to fit with his conception of of knowledge. Another example can be drawn from another way that &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; are problematically instrumental: they can be misused, put to work thwarting their natural ends as well as advancing them, as Socrates points out in the &lt;em&gt;Hippias Minor&lt;/em&gt;. Aristotle gives this as a reason for saying that virtue is not a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;; some scholars think Socrates is trying to make that point too.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:44&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:44&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;44&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But in fact, as I will explain in §2, the denial of &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt; ensures that virtue will not &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; be abused, so Socrates already has a way out of this problem, without giving up the view that virtue is a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. Plato later takes a different approach, since in the &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; he accepts the reality of &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt;. But the &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; emphasizes the role of practice and experience in &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;; a substantial portion of the &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; discusses cultivation of the character that is a prerequisite for moral knowledge. And this means that even though Plato makes conceptual space for &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt;, his understanding of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;-possession allows him to hold that virtue is knowledge, and that knowledge is &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, but again without the implication that virtue might be abused. So in neither case does the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;-model itself need to be rejected or relegated to a lesser role.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:45&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:45&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;45&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;techne-and-propositional-knowledge&quot;&gt;Techne and Propositional Knowledge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Protagoras&lt;/em&gt;, Socrates and Protagoras discuss the claim, attributed to the many, that one can know what one should do, and yet not do it. Socrates and Protagoras disagree with the many; they think that knowledge is “strong” and would not succumb to temptation that way. And this seems to be an explicit discussion of the nature of knowledge in the context of an example of &lt;em&gt;propositional knowledge&lt;/em&gt;. So how does the existence of such discussions fit with my claim that, for Socrates, knowledge just is &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;? To begin answering that question, it’s best to begin with this very treatment of &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;Protagoras&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates argues that &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt; is impossible. The argument is framed as a refutation of the many, who &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; believe in &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt;: they believe that, thinking you should do one thing, you can be “overwhelmed” by fear or the prospect of some pleasure, and act contrary to your better judgement.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:46&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:46&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;46&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Socrates first foists hedonism on his opponents—the best action, they would agree, is the most pleasant action, or the action most productive of pleasure over time. But then, given hedonism, for some pleasure to overwhelm you is for some &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; to overwhelm you. And this good which “overwhelms” you must not be the greater good, or you would not be doing anything wrong by pursuing it. So being overwhelmed must entail choosing lesser goods over greater. But Socrates finds this unintelligible, since there is no longer a question of being deceived by pleasures and pains distinct from the goods and evils in question (255d–e).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:47&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:47&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;47&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Or again, by hedonism, being overwhelmed would have to mean choosing lesser pleasures over greater. But, says Socrates, there is nothing more to comparing the values of two sets of pleasures and pains than weighing them up against each other, and weighing is treated as a purely quantitative matter (256a). So now again, Socrates thinks, there is nothing here to be overwhelmed by: it is not intelligible that a person would choose a set of pleasures which they see to be the smaller. &lt;em&gt;Akrasia,&lt;/em&gt; then, is impossible. Whatever you believe it best to do you will in fact do.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:48&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:48&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;48&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in Socrates’ view, to believe that some course of action is best is largely worthless from the perspective of producing that action. The “power of appearances,” we are told, causes us “to wander and to change back and forth, to accept and reject the same things in actions and in choices of large and small” (i.e. large and small pleasures; &lt;em&gt;Protagoras&lt;/em&gt; 356d). So we do what we believe best—but we are easily misled, and we easily change our minds. (You have resolved to avoid unhealthy foods, but the offer of a tempting dessert prompts you to make an exception, since after all it would be rude to refuse—but immediately the thing is consumed, you know that your host would have been perfectly understanding.)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:49&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:49&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;49&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beliefs are not strictly &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; unstable or untrustworthy. In the &lt;em&gt;Crito&lt;/em&gt; Socrates tells the eponymous character that we should be attentive to the beliefs of wise people rather than to those of foolish people (46d–47b). It is to the knowledgeable that things will appear as they are—a point also of the &lt;em&gt;Gorgias.&lt;/em&gt; Now the wise are not wise merely on account of having the right views; rather they may be expected to have the right views—i.e. the right beliefs—because they are wise. And it thus matters a great deal whether we ourselves have the wisdom that ensures we see things the right way, especially given the denial of &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just the point Socrates goes on to make in the &lt;em&gt;Protagoras.&lt;/em&gt; Here the issue is knowledge of the good in general, and after describing the instability of mere belief, Socrates says that our “salvation” will be a “craft of measurement,” which would&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;render the appearance ineffective: by making clear the truth, it would &amp;gt; cause the soul to be at peace by abiding in the truth, and so save our &amp;gt; life. (356d–e)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates says that this moral master-&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; is a mathematical one (since it involves measurement), and indeed he identifies it with arithmetic (357a).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:50&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:50&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;50&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But the general point of importance for us is the role of knowledge—and specifically &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;—in ensuring correct beliefs in particular cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beliefs have many sources besides one’s own expertise: wishful thinking, sadness or anger, nearby pleasures or faraway pains, optical illusions, the advice of experts or of charlatans. These forces sometimes compete, and some are stronger than others. So, in the speeches of Phaedrus and Agathon in the &lt;em&gt;Symposium,&lt;/em&gt; love dominates other emotions: fear would not drive you from battle while you fight beside your beloved. Likewise, in the &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt;, Socrates concedes that the testimony of the orator, who knows how to play on the emotions, will, among the ignorant, be more compelling than the testimony of a genuine expert. But, according to Socrates, knowledge (if you possess it yourself) dominates all other sources of belief. That is what he means by saying that knowledge is &lt;em&gt;strong,&lt;/em&gt; as he puts it in the &lt;em&gt;Protagoras&lt;/em&gt; (352b): without a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, your beliefs are at the mercy of other forces; if you possess a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, you will think the right way about the appropriate cases.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:51&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:51&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;51&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the original dispute between Socrates and the many was actually about whether it is possible to &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; what to do &lt;em&gt;in a particular case&lt;/em&gt; and yet not to do it. Can you know, say, that you ought to get out of bed right now, but not do it because the blankets are so warm? As we have now seen, Socrates’ response is two-fold: first he argues against the possibility of &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt;, and then he explains how a hypothetical &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; of measurement would ensure that the comfort of the warm blanket won’t fool you into thinking you should stay in bed. The result is that your craft knowledge delivers you (and allows you to maintain) the correct belief that you ought to get up, or—to fall in line with the way the many originally made their claim—the (propositional) knowledge that you ought to get up.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:52&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:52&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;52&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Crito&lt;/em&gt; Socrates calls the views that stem from (craft) knowledge “good beliefs,” but sometimes he simply calls such views &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt;, just as the many talked of knowledge of particular facts in the &lt;em&gt;Protagoras.&lt;/em&gt; Thus we see Socrates asking Ion whether each of them don’t know that Socrates has five fingers on his hand “by the same craft, that of arithmetic”? (537e). That is, because you know (the craft of) arithmetic, you can know (the fact that) there are five fingers on a hand.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:53&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:53&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;53&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Likewise the charioteer will be the one to judge advice on racing, and so also the doctor and the pilot in their respective spheres (537). We therefore find that in different senses &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; knowledge and &lt;em&gt;is a source of&lt;/em&gt; knowledge.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:54&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:54&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;54&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But of course the fact that Socrates is often interested in knowledge which represents the exercise of a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; should not be permitted to obscure the centrality of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; in his epistemological thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-varieties-of-knowledge&quot;&gt;Other Varieties of Knowledge?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it must be allowed that Socrates also talks about, or attributes, knowledge even where no (actually possessed) &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; seems to be in question. For example, Charmides knows Greek (&lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt; 159a); in the &lt;em&gt;Apology&lt;/em&gt; Socrates says: “to do injustice and disobey my superior, this I know to be evil and base” (29b); in the &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; he says “I know well that if you will agree with me on those things which my soul believes, those things will be the very truth” (486e). So if knowedge is &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, what’s happening in passages such as these?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates’ claims to moral knowledge may be thought particularly problematic. Although Socrates occasionally claims moral knowledge, he also disavows moral knowledge in sweeping terms. After examining one politician, Socrates reflects as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am indeed wiser than he. It is unlikely that either of us knows &amp;gt; anything noble or good, but he thinks that he knows something which he &amp;gt; does not know, whereas, as I don’t actually know, neither do I think I &amp;gt; do. (&lt;em&gt;Apology&lt;/em&gt; 21d)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; we find him saying flatly, “I confess to my shame that I have no knowledge at all about virtue” (71d). I read these statements as disavowals of a moral &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, as when Socrates denies having that &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, claimed by others, which would allow him to train children in goodness (e.g. at &lt;em&gt;Apology&lt;/em&gt; 19e–20c, &lt;em&gt;Laches&lt;/em&gt; 186a–c). So it would seem that Socrates’ confidence on specific moral questions &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; be founded on possession of a moral &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, Socrates apparently supposes that you cannot know anything about e.g. virtue without knowing what virtue is (which I take to mean that without possessing the virtue-&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; you cannot know anything about virtue), and also that you cannot know whether something is e.g. admirable (&lt;em&gt;kalon&lt;/em&gt;) without knowing what the admirable &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. without having the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; which takes the admirable as its object).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:55&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:55&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;55&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; So not only does Socrates claim knowledge where there seems to be no &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, he claims knowledge where he &lt;em&gt;disavows&lt;/em&gt; the appropriate &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, and even says that, lacking such expertise, he &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt; have any knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some scholars have felt that there is a genuine &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt; here—a tension or contradiction between the avowals and the disavowals of knowledge. They suggest that different dialogues reveal diverging epistemological standards, or that some apparent knowledge claims can be treated as somehow anomalous.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:56&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:56&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;56&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But such manuevers seem to me unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose someone asked me what I knew about category theory, in such a way as to make me suspect he had an interest in learning about it. Probably I would say that I knew nothing about it; maybe that “I don’t know the first thing about it.” But if some nerdy party game required me to list the things I know about category theory, well, then: its name starts with a ‘C’; it’s a highly abstract logical-mathematical system; its connectives are very powerful. And it is perfectly ordinary and intelligible that I should in this way be able to say both that I know nothing about category theory and that I know lots of things about category theory. Philosophically speaking, there are different ways we might sort out my claims. We might invoke some form of contextualist semantics for knowledge attribution, whereby different standards are established by different conversational settings. Or we might distinguish different senses of ‘know,’ so that in one sense of ‘know’ I might know that P if I have it on good testimony; in another sense I might know that P only if I can explain why it is that P. Again, we might say that there is a difference in the kinds of things I am claiming to know: in the first case I am claiming to know a particular fact, and in the second case denying that I’m familiar with a subject matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bearing in mind plausible strategies of these sorts, I do not see any need to be very concerned about inconsistencies between Socrates’ various attributions of knowledge. And indeed the issue for most scholars has been not so much to worry that Socrates’ various knowledge claims and ascriptions are contradictory, but to determine &lt;em&gt;what sort of knowledge&lt;/em&gt; Socrates is avowing when he avows knowledge, and &lt;em&gt;what sort of knowledge&lt;/em&gt; he is disavowing when he disavows knowledge.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:57&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:57&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;57&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it would be a mistake to attribute &lt;em&gt;to Socrates himself&lt;/em&gt; a &lt;em&gt;reflective conception&lt;/em&gt; of any form of knowledge besides &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. What there are in the early dialogues are attributions of knowledge which do not fit the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;-conception. But to find in such knowledge-attributions a &lt;em&gt;conception of a form of knowledge&lt;/em&gt; would be to find a Socratic form of knowledge which would have to be “characterized almost entirely in negative terms.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:58&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:58&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;58&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; And contrast with the fairly clear and demanding standards for craft knowledge, Socrates would apparently have &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; particular criteria for any sort of non-expert knowledge.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:59&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:59&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;59&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; At best we might hope to identify some ways Socrates thinks you could come by such knowledge—by divine revelation, perhaps, or as derived from a life’s experience interrogating others.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:60&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:60&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say “I know X,” and thereby to claim knowledge of some form—with however much confidence or care or sincerity—is not thereby to deploy a conception of that form of knowledge. It does not amount to having a view about that form of knowledge or even to distinguishing it from others. Socrates talks about knowing &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt;, people, inanimate objects, qualities, and languages, but that is not cause for supposing either that he thinks these all involve the same sort of knowledge or that he has conceptions of five different types of knowledge. Perhaps Socrates &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; have distinguished, say, the kind of knowledge a craftsman has from the (propositional, factual) knowledge which the (merely) experienced person has. Later Aristotle did just that (e.g. &lt;em&gt;Metaphysics&lt;/em&gt; 981a28–30). But Socrates only spoke a language for which such distinctions &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be drawn.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:61&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:61&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;61&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may decide that the Socratic conception of knowledge is defective in some way, or that it covers only a limited range of the epistemological phenomena, and we may even think that some of his own claims to knowledge show this. We could say that his attributions of knowledge are actually incoherent, or we could defend the coherence of his attributions by invoking a contextualist semantics. But my topic is Socrates’ &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; conception or conceptions of knowledge. And as far as I can see, the only variety of knowledge of which he has any conception is &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;knowledge-as-techne&quot;&gt;Knowledge as Techne&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen thus far that Socrates has a distinctive and reflective conception of at least one form of knowledge, namely &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. We’ve also seen that a lot of Socrates’ epistemological reflections should be understood within the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;-framework. Thus the interest in knowing “what things are” reflects one of Socrates criteria for &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;-possession; propositional knowledge is often the manifestation of expertise. And while many references to knowledge in the early dialogues cannot be understood in terms of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, they do not go so far as to indicate that Socrates recognizes different varieties of knowledge. But to establish my claim that, in Socrates mind, knowledge is &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, I ought to show some &lt;em&gt;positive tendency&lt;/em&gt; on his part to interpret knowledge as &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. I give some illustrations of just such a tendency here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One example we have already touched on is from the &lt;em&gt;Protagoras.&lt;/em&gt; There Socrates sets out to show that knowledge (&lt;em&gt;episteme&lt;/em&gt;) is strong, rather than weak, as the many suppose (352b). This is proved precisely by showing that a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; (specifically a craft of measurement) will ensure that you get things right (at 356a–357e). So Socrates proves his point with the assumption that ‘&lt;em&gt;episteme&lt;/em&gt;’ may be replaced by ‘&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.’&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:62&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:62&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Now ‘&lt;em&gt;episteme&lt;/em&gt;’ is indeed frequently synonymous with ‘&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;’ in the Socratic dialogues, but if Socrates is thinking of &lt;em&gt;episteme&lt;/em&gt; in terms of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; right from the start at 352b, that would itself be surprising.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:63&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:63&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;63&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The issue between Socrates and the many at that point is not the value of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; but the effect of knowing &lt;em&gt;what the right action in given circumstances&lt;/em&gt; is (see esp. 352d). But Socrates &lt;em&gt;treats&lt;/em&gt; the view of the many as a challenge to the value of knowledge &lt;em&gt;taken as&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is at &lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt; 165, where Critias proposes that temperance is knowing oneself. Socrates says that if temperance is knowing (&lt;em&gt;gignoskein&lt;/em&gt;), then it must be some kind of &lt;em&gt;episteme&lt;/em&gt;, and it must be &lt;em&gt;of something&lt;/em&gt;; his examples are medicine and housebuilding, which are ‘of’ health and building houses respectively. Though he then grants (at 166a) that knowledge need not &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; have a product (as evidenced by mathematical knowledge), Socrates continues to assume that knowledge must be useful. So here again we have an immediate transition from knowledge to &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; (‘&lt;em&gt;episteme&lt;/em&gt;’ is here equivalent to ‘&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;,’ which also appears several times in this passage). It is notable how peculiar this transition is: Socrates apparently supposes that self-knowledge could only be interpreted as some kind of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, despite the fact that there is &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt; no &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; in the neighborhood—as the rest of the dialogue makes clear enough—nor any evident reason to suppose right at the start that there should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt; example is also interesting on account of the vocabulary employed. According to John Lyon’s analysis of Plato’s epistemological vocabulary, the verbs ‘&lt;em&gt;eidenai&lt;/em&gt;,’ ‘&lt;em&gt;epistasthai&lt;/em&gt;,’ and ‘&lt;em&gt;gignoskein&lt;/em&gt;’ are grouped in the following way: ‘&lt;em&gt;eidenai&lt;/em&gt;’ is largely interchangeably with either ‘&lt;em&gt;epistasthai&lt;/em&gt;’ or ‘&lt;em&gt;gignoskein&lt;/em&gt;,’ but ‘&lt;em&gt;epistasthai&lt;/em&gt;’ and ‘&lt;em&gt;gignoskein&lt;/em&gt;’ are not themselves interchangeable.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:64&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:64&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;64&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; And ‘&lt;em&gt;epistasthai&lt;/em&gt;’ and ‘&lt;em&gt;gignoskein&lt;/em&gt;’ play somewhat different roles. For example, ‘&lt;em&gt;gignoskein&lt;/em&gt;,’ unlike ‘&lt;em&gt;epistasthai&lt;/em&gt;,’ is particularly associated with personal nouns,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:65&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:65&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;65&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; while ‘&lt;em&gt;epistasthai&lt;/em&gt;’ is in general a “generator” for ‘&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;,’ in the sense that if someone knows in the sense of &lt;em&gt;epistasthai&lt;/em&gt;, then you can invoke a corresponding &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:66&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:66&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;66&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Now in the &lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt; passage, we move from ‘&lt;em&gt;gignoskein&lt;/em&gt;’ to ‘&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.’ But the example is not at odds with Lyons’ analysis. Socrates only speaks of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; after eliciting from Critias some examples of what are in fact conventional &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt;, but under the heading of ‘&lt;em&gt;episteme&lt;/em&gt;,’ and this may very well reflect the fact that ‘&lt;em&gt;gignoskein&lt;/em&gt;’ is not so naturally associated with ‘&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.’ What we see here is an &lt;em&gt;inference&lt;/em&gt; on Socrates’ part: we have a case of knowing something (&lt;em&gt;gignoskein ti&lt;/em&gt;) and &lt;em&gt;therefore&lt;/em&gt; also of &lt;em&gt;episteme&lt;/em&gt; and then &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. And this shows that Socrates is prepared to infer a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; not only where the sort of knowledge in question (knowing oneself) seems to have no evident connection with &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, but also where the specific epistemic vocabulary has no particular connection with &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; in general Platonic usage.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:67&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:67&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;67&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Ion&lt;/em&gt; furnishes another example we’ve touched on. At 537c–e Socrates is discussing the way different &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; have different subject matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Take these fingers: I know there are five of them, and you know the &amp;gt; same thing about them that I do. Now suppose I ask you whether it’s &amp;gt; the same craft—that of arithmetic—that teaches you and me the same &amp;gt; things, or whether it’s two different ones. Of course you’d say it’s &amp;gt; the same one.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:68&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:68&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;68&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not surprising that &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; comes up here, because that’s the topic, but the suggestion that it’s in virtue of a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; that we know something so simple as that we have five fingers is interesting—it certainly isn’t the case that anyone who can count to five is a mathematician. So Socrates seems quite prepared to subsume very mundane sorts of knowledge under &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That suggests another general point: Socrates doesn’t concern himself with knowledge that can come &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; in bits and pieces, such as historical knowledge.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:69&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:69&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;69&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Now the lack of discussion of such knowledge doesn’t prove much on its own, since Socrates’ emphasis on moral knowledge will naturally make practical varieties of knowledge more prominent.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:70&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:70&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;70&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But we can sharpen the point by considering the treatment of poetry and oratory. Not only does Socrates not consider these &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt;, he never considers the possibility that they might still involve impressive bodies of psychological or dramatic knowledge—though there were, after all, rhetorical &lt;em&gt;manuals.&lt;/em&gt; The choices seem to be: &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; or nothing. We can see this at &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; 464c-465a, where it’s clear that to say that rhetoric (or here “flattery,” of which rhetoric is a sub-type) is not a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;thereby&lt;/em&gt; to say that it &lt;em&gt;just guesses.&lt;/em&gt; This is typical for Socrates: if you’re having success, then it’s because of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, or else merely a result of guessing or divine inspiration or madness.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:71&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:71&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;71&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know that such examples could be considered decisive. If poets and orators were claiming a special ability as educators, then perhaps it was appropriate to hold them to high standards. And perhaps the &lt;em&gt;Protagoras&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt; examples could be put down to Socrates’ penchant for appealing to &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; whenever virtue is in question. But on the whole I think that there is a good case here for saying that, for Socrates, knowledge &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. To be sure, Socrates does claim knowledge, or attribute it to others, in other contexts. And Socrates cannot be said to have distinguished craft knowledge from any other sort of knowledge. &lt;em&gt;Euthyphro&lt;/em&gt; 6e, for example, seems to have propositional knowledge, acquaintance, and &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; all jumbled together. But Socrates’ thought tends strongly in the direction of craft knowledge, and this is really no surprise, since it’s the only sort of knowledge of which he has any definite and developed conception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-looking-forward&quot;&gt;Conclusion: Looking Forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conception of knowledge I have described is easy enough to overlook. For us it’s an unfamiliar conception, developed in the context of unfamiliar debates. It’s a problematic conception of knowledge as well, since the treatment of virtue as &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; creates difficulties made plain even in the dialogues themselves. The role of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; is further obscured by the room it makes for propositional knowledge, by the fact that Socrates’ conception of knowledge doesn’t entirely constrain his epistemological language, and by the fact that Socratic method is more prominent than Socratic theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may also be thought that the identification of knowledge and &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; is at any rate peculiar to Plato’s earlier dialogues. The &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; in particular is (rightly) seen as a “transitional” dialogue, in which more distinctively Platonic, as opposed to Socratic, epistemological themes are emerging. But in fact the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;-model is no less important in the &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; (for example) than in earlier dialogues. Socrates and Plato do grapple with difficulties presented by the model, or by the uses they put it to. New epistemological themes do emerge. But this is only to say that Plato eventually saw the need for a &lt;em&gt;modified&lt;/em&gt; understanding of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To vindicate that claim I would need to defend a detailed interpretation of the epistemology of the &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; and other dialogues. Here I will settle for illustrating one way in which Plato seems to have been motivated to rework the Socratic conception of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:72&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:72&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;72&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can start with the observation of Paul Woodruff (whose view of Socratic epistemology is in many ways similar to my own) that whereas learning is in the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; said to be a matter of recollection, and thus involves no teaching, teachability was a mark of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:73&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:73&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;73&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; He thinks that the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;-model for knowledge has therefore been abandoned by the time of the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that seems hasty. Is geometry no longer a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;? Does Socrates imagine a future for geometry without teachers? Or if teachers must now be known as ‘people who inspire recollection,’ have we abandoned the teachability criterion or only come to a new understanding of ‘teaching’?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:74&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:74&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;74&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Or couldn’t Plato be toying with new ideas about how &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; are acquired?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:75&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:75&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;75&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a more substantial point. The proposal that learning is actually recollection is a response to the paradox of inquiry, posed by Meno in two parts at 80d: how will you search for something if you don’t know what it is? And how will you recognize it even if you find it? This paradox is a sophistical trick, as Socrates points out. And yet Plato makes use of the paradox to introduce recollection. And one reason for this is that the paradox is a genuine problem given the Socratic conception of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Varieties of the paradox of inquiry already manifest themselves in earlier dialogues. At the start of the &lt;em&gt;Protagoras,&lt;/em&gt; we find Socrates cautioning Hippocrates, who wishes to learn wisdom from Protagoras. As it happens, Hippocrates can’t say just what it is that Protagoras teaches—he suggests lamely that Protagoras will teach him “about what [Protagoras] knows” (312e). Socrates warns Hippocrates that a sophist is “a sort of merchant or pedlar of goods for the nourishment of the soul,” but that sophists don’t know whether their merchandise is of any value—and this is a danger because you can’t even take the sophist’s goods to an expert for inspection before you consume them. Hippocrates is in a predicament: he has a vague notion that wisdom is desirable thing, but no way to pursue it. He can’t safely go to a teacher unless he already possess the expertise he would learn.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:76&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:76&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;76&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt; generalizes the point: only a craftsman will be able to tell whether another claimant to the same &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; is or is not an impostor (170d–c). This is perhaps not a very serious problem, if a problem at all, when it comes to, say, weaving, but it might be a problem with something like medicine (to which Socrates appeals in the &lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt;), at least in the ancient world, with its rival schools of medicine. If we add the point from the &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; that only a doctor can reliably distinguish genuine health from merely apparent health (464a), then we could again pose Meno’s question: supposing you think that health is a good thing, but don’t &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; health after the fashion of a doctor, how will you learn what it is?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:77&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:77&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;77&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the really pressing case is &lt;em&gt;virtue&lt;/em&gt;. Besides the general problem about inquiry, there is here the problem that there seem to be no authentic teachers at all—a point emphasized in the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:78&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:78&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;78&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Socrates was perhaps prepared to accept that no moral &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; was attainable, and to satisfy himself with going about on his divine mission, showing that anyone who claimed such a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; was a fraud (&lt;em&gt;Apology&lt;/em&gt; 23b). But Plato, as the &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; shows, evidently had higher hopes. The difficulties gave him a reason to figure out a new view, and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a reason to stop being interested in expertise. This meant, among other things, an emphasis on the &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt;, a corresponding shift in how the objects of &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; are understood metaphysically (i.e. as Forms), and thus also a greater emphasis on &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; like geometry which are more readily interpretable in those terms. But that’s the start of another story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix-two-examples-in-the-meno&quot;&gt;Appendix: Two Examples in the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; will make it clear that stability is a mark of knowledge in general, as opposed to just moral knowledge (98a).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earlier dialogues generally have the moral life particularly in view, but the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; makes it clear that belief in general is changeable, by contrast with knowledge: on its own, whether true or false, belief is unstable and flighty, and Socrates likens beliefs to runaway slaves, or the unsecured statues of Daedelus (97c–98b).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:79&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:79&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;79&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twice above I appealed to a passage in the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; which I take to indicate that features of beliefs and [&lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt;] which I identified as holding in at least some specific cases are indeed features of belief and knowledge generally. In that passage, at 98a, it is said that beliefs become knowledge when tied down with “an account of the reason why.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:80&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:80&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;80&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This statement will naturally seem to treat primarily of atomic knowledge, to suggest that it is analyzable partly in terms of belief, and to concern itself with what is added to belief to get knowledge. And it is not obvious that there is anything to do with [techne] lurking here. So one could fairly wonder whether knowledge here in this passage has anything to do with the form of knowledge I’ve been discussing, and whether this passage doesn’t offer (or at least suggest) a different account of atomic knowledge than the one I just proposed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If at 98a Plato is primarily concerned with an analysis of knowledge in terms of beliefs, that would mark a departure from the earlier centrality of [techne]. The passage does certainly describe a process whereby beliefs become knowledge. However, this process is rather opaque, since the phrase “an account of the reason why” (or “the cause”), is not terribly perspicuous. But, like most scholars, I take it to imply that knowledge requires some kind of understanding, or a capacity to explain why things are as they are. That seems to be borne out by Socrates identification of account giving with recollection—which is to say that he identifies giving an account with the sort of thing Meno’s slave had embarked on earlier in the dialogue.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:81&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:81&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;81&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In that earlier conversation, Socrates and the slave together go through a demonstration to the effect that, taking one square, a second square of twice the area can be constructed by taking the diagonal of the first as a side of the second. But Socrates does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; say that the slave then knows that this can be done. Rather he says that “these opinions have now just been stirred up like a dream, but if he were repeatedly asked these same questions in various ways, you know that in the end his knowledge about these things would be as accurate as anyone’s” (85c-d). Now this hardly tells us &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what or how much more the slave would have to understand before he could be said to know any geometry, but it certainly suggests that Socrates is not interested just in knowledge of particular, isolated facts, but in facility with a &lt;em&gt;bodies&lt;/em&gt; of knowledge, as in the earlier dialogues. A continued interest in [techne] would account for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That very tentative conclusion may be supported by the observation that although “account of the reason why” ([&lt;em&gt;aitias logismos&lt;/em&gt;]) is not very perspicuous on its own, it is suggestive of the discussions of [techne] in the &lt;em&gt;Gorgias.&lt;/em&gt; At 465a we have Socrates saying that “cookery”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;is not a craft, but a knack, because it has no rational account (&lt;em&gt;logos&lt;/em&gt;) by which it applies the things it applies, to say what they are by nature, so that it cannot say what is the explanation (&lt;em&gt;aitia&lt;/em&gt;) of each thing. (Irwin trans.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is reiterated at 501a with the example of medicine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I said that medicine has considered the nature of what it cares for &amp;gt; and the explanation (&lt;em&gt;aitia&lt;/em&gt;) of what it does, and can give a rational &amp;gt; account (&lt;em&gt;logos&lt;/em&gt;) of each of these things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could be that, in the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt;, Plato is not committed to the [techne] model in particular, but that he remains committed to the place of explanatory facility in knowledge generally. Still, this is at least a point of continuity, and at best it offers us (the readers, if not Meno) a way of interpreting an otherwise fairly opaque remark about knowledge. The kind of explanatory ability required here would then be the general capacity to explain the principles and applications of a body of knowledge defining a [techne], at least so far as relevant to the particular beliefs in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having said that, we could certainly also say—and I do not believe Plato would be averse to saying—that once the slave becomes expert in geometry, he will know things which previously he only believed, by tying the old beliefs down with the explanations he now has at hand. So the beliefs at 98a might themselves become instances of atomic knowledge when their possessor can give the right sort of account. But if I am right, it would remain the case that, for beliefs to become knowledge, you would effectively have to add &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; to them—that is, [techne] or some degree thereof.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:82&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:82&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;82&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It would then remain the case that there is knowledge of the atomic sort only in the presence of [techne], in the way described above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is certainly true that, between the idea of recollection and the idea of somehow developing knowledge by way of belief, there is something new in the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; in terms epistemology. And that demands explanation. I do not believe that the correct explanation reveals the abandonment of the [techne] model. But I defer this and related issues for my conclusion.\&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two prominent epistemological examples in the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; don’t fit easily with the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;-model, so I wish to address them briefly. The first occurs at 71b, where Socrates says that he couldn’t know what qualities Meno possesses (say looks or riches) if he didn’t know who Meno was. Socrates uses the example to illustrate the point that he can’t say whether virtue can be taught since he doesn’t know what virtue is. The other is the ‘road to Larissa’ example [CITE]. This example is mean to illustrate the equal practical efficacy of knowledge and true belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidently neither Meno nor the road to Larissa is suitable material for a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, just as there is no &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; dealing with the poems of Homer in particular. Moreover the latter example has been cited to show that knowledge is “a state improved with regard to the very same things that the unimproved state [i.e. belief] is concerned with.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:83&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:83&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;83&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Whereas I have resisted (except in relation to atomic knowledge) the sort of ‘analysis of knowledge in terms of belief’ interpretation which this might suggest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now although neither example fits the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;-model, they don’t very well fit the epistemology of the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; as a whole, either, as Dominic @scott2006psm points out regarding the road to Larissa case. This is because it’s not clear what knowing Meno or knowing the road to Larissa has to do with either recollection or explanation. And since it seems clear that the examples don’t really suit the epistemological outlook of &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt;, it seems unnecessary to worry too much about them not suiting the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;-model.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:84&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:84&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;84&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The fact that Plato is quite happy to use these particular examples speaks more to the fact that Plato does not distinguish forms of knowledge the way we might than to the direction of his epistemological thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One the other hand, even if knowledge of Meno or the road to Larissa is not systematic or explanatory in a way befitting a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, there are affinities. Part of the point of the examples is presumably that knowing Meno or the road entails a degree of familiarity, and knowledge of the thing will entail, or be the source of, a great deal of &lt;em&gt;further&lt;/em&gt; knowledge. As a doctor recognizes ailments by their symptoms, someone who knows Meno will be able to recognize him, too. Knowing medicine means knowing various specific techniques; knowing a road means knowing its twists and turns, and knowing Meno means knowing things &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; him. And we could expect knowledge of the road to Larissa to be reliable, in something like the way &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; is. (If you’ve travelled the road to Larissa often, it’s unlikely someone could talk you into changing your view as to whether it goes through Chalcis.) So the examples share enough features (at least arguably) with the sort of systematic and explanatory knowledge Plato &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; primarily interested in that they can serve to make the points Plato wants to make.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:85&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:85&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;85&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about the point that the road to Larissa example shows that knowledge and belief have a common object. It is less tempting to say here again that the examples are only imperfect illustrations of the sort of knowledge Plato is really concerned with, because other examples could be adduced, such as the case where Socrates says (at 85c–d) that the slave could come to know what he now only believes.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:86&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:86&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;86&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But experience with the earlier dialogues offers us a fine response.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:87&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:87&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;87&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Plato just isn’t fastidious about, if cognizant at all of, the difference between knowledge of the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; as a whole and knowledge about aspects of the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; or about applications of the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. In the latter cases, knowledge may very well be constituted by belief, and that’s enough to account for the fact that the same objects are sometimes spoken of as objects of both belief and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J. Allen. Failure and Expertise in the Ancient Conception of an Art. &lt;em&gt;Scientific Failure&lt;/em&gt;, 1994.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R. E. Allen. The Socratic Paradox. &lt;em&gt;Journal of the History of Ideas&lt;/em&gt;, 21(2): 256–265, 1960.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R. E. Allen. &lt;em&gt;The Dialogues of Plato, vol. 1: Euthyphro, Apology, Crito, Meno, Gorgias, Menexenus&lt;/em&gt;. Yale University Press, 1989.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R. E. Allen. &lt;em&gt;The Dialogues of Plato, vol. 3: Ion, Hippias Minor, Laches, Protagoras&lt;/em&gt;. Yale University Press, 1996.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugh Benson. &lt;em&gt;Socratic Wisdom: The Model of Knowledge in Platos Early Dialogues&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford University Press, 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T. C. Brickhouse and N. D. Smith. &lt;em&gt;Platos Socrates&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford University Press, 1994.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E. R. Dodds. &lt;em&gt;Plato Gorgias&lt;/em&gt;. Clarendon Press Oxford, England, 1959.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A.I. Goldman. Experts: which ones should you trust? &lt;em&gt;Philosophy and Phenomenological Research&lt;/em&gt;, pages 85–110, 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J. Gosling. &lt;em&gt;Platos Moral Theory&lt;/em&gt;. Philosophical Books, 19:97–102, 1978.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;F. Heinimann. Eine vorplatonische Theorie der . &lt;em&gt;Museum Helveticum&lt;/em&gt;, 18:105–130, 1961.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T. Irwin. &lt;em&gt;Platos Moral Theory: the Early and Middle Dialogues&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford University Press, 1977.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T. Irwin. &lt;em&gt;Plato: Gorgias&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford, 1979.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T. Irwin. &lt;em&gt;Platos Ethics&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford University Press, 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C. H. Kahn. &lt;em&gt;Plato and the Socratic Dialogue&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge University Press, 1996.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Kraut. &lt;em&gt;Socrates and the State&lt;/em&gt;. Princeton University Press, 1984.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Lyons. &lt;em&gt;Structural Semantics&lt;/em&gt;. Blackwell, 1972.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jessica Moss. Pleasure and Illusion in Plato. &lt;em&gt;Philosophy and Phenomenological Research&lt;/em&gt;, 72(3):503–535, 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander Nehamas. Menos Paradox and Socrates as a Teacher. &lt;em&gt;Virtues of Authenticity&lt;/em&gt;, 1999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terry Penner. Socrates on the Strength of Knowledge: Protagoras 351b- 357e. &lt;em&gt;Archiv für Geschichte der Philosophie&lt;/em&gt;, 79:117–149, 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C. D. C. Reeve. &lt;em&gt;Socrates in the Apology&lt;/em&gt;. Hackett, 1989.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Roochnik. Socratess Use of the Techne-Analogy. &lt;em&gt;Journal of the History of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;, 24(3):295–310, 1986.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Roochnik. Counting on Number: Plato on the Goodness of Arithmos. &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Philology&lt;/em&gt;, 115(4):543–563, 1994.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Roochnik. &lt;em&gt;Of Art and Wisdom&lt;/em&gt;. Pennsylvania State University Press, 1996.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Schiefsky. &lt;em&gt;Hippocrates: On Ancient Medicine&lt;/em&gt;. Brill, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angela Smith. Knowledge and Expertise in the Early Platonic Dialogues. &lt;em&gt;Archiv für Geschichte Der Philosophie&lt;/em&gt;, 80(2), 1998.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gregory Vlastos. Ethics and Physics in Democritus. Part II. &lt;em&gt;The Philosopical Review&lt;/em&gt;, 55:53–64, 1946.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Woodruff. Platos Early Theory of Knowledge. &lt;em&gt;Epistemology&lt;/em&gt;, 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;@huemer2002ecr, p. 1. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;By “earlier dialogues,” I mean the &lt;em&gt;Apology, Charmides, Crito, Euthydemus, Euthyphro, Gorgias, Hippias Major, Hippias Minor, Ion, Laches, Lysis,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Protagoras&lt;/em&gt;; I also draw on the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; I. (But similar examples are also prominent in later dialogues.) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; 491a; &lt;em&gt;Memorabilia&lt;/em&gt; 1.2. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;@vlastos1991socrates [p. 41]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;@benson2000swm [11]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;pp. 211–212. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;@irwin1995pse [70]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Isocrates’ &lt;em&gt;Against the Sophists&lt;/em&gt; and the Hippocratic &lt;em&gt;On Ancient Medicine&lt;/em&gt; discuss oratory and medicine respectively. @heinimann1961vpt treats the situation prior to Plato. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;181e–184c. Neither Laches nor Nicias actually uses the word ‘&lt;em&gt;techne,&lt;/em&gt;’ when speaking of fighting in armour; rather they refer to it as a (possible) subject (&lt;em&gt;mathema&lt;/em&gt;), or as knowledge (&lt;em&gt;episteme&lt;/em&gt;). Now ‘&lt;em&gt;episteme&lt;/em&gt;’ is a frequent synonym for ‘&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;’ in the early dialogues. And Socrates is treating ‘&lt;em&gt;mathema&lt;/em&gt;’ as implying a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; at 185e, and when he begins speaking of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; back at 185a, Nicias assumes that the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; in question would be fighting in armour (185c). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;@schiefsky2005 [63–4] argues for dating &lt;em&gt;VM&lt;/em&gt; to the late fifth century. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A few scholars have recently taken more of an interest in the Socratic conception of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; in its own right, and as a matter of &lt;em&gt;epistemology&lt;/em&gt; rather than just ethics—most notably Paul @woodruff1990pse and Angela @asmith1998. A useful discussion with more attention to the contemporary views about &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; may be found in @reeve1989sita [37–45], though Reeve’s discussion generally gives the (in my view mistaken) impression that there was &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; going view of &lt;em&gt;techne,&lt;/em&gt; albeit one which underwent some development. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;449d. Trans. Zeyl. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On systematicity see also @woodruff1990pse [71–2], @asmith1998 [135–6]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:14&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;cf. @kahn1996pas [xx]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:14&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:15&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Arithmetic is a special case, representing an ideal of precision (&lt;em&gt;akribeia&lt;/em&gt;)—see @roochnik1994cnp [@roochnik1996aaw] and @schiefsky2005 [13–18]. Indeed Plato will later say that every &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; must participate in &lt;em&gt;arithmos&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;logistike&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; 522c; cf. &lt;em&gt;Philebus&lt;/em&gt; 55e ff.). But exceptional or not, my point holds. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:15&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:16&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;@allen1994 provides an excellent survey of this topic. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:16&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:17&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;@roochnik1986 [19–20]. Cf. Isocrates (&lt;em&gt;Against the Sophists&lt;/em&gt;) on writing out letters. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:17&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:18&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For this sort of objection see e.g. &lt;em&gt;Protagoras&lt;/em&gt; 319a–320b, &lt;em&gt;Laches&lt;/em&gt; 185d–e, Isocrates &lt;em&gt;Against the Sophists&lt;/em&gt; 14, &lt;em&gt;Dissoi Logoi&lt;/em&gt; 6.5–6, &lt;em&gt;De Arte&lt;/em&gt; 4; cf. @heinimann1961vpt [123–6]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:18&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:19&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; 448c, &lt;em&gt;Euthydemus&lt;/em&gt; 279ff., &lt;em&gt;De Arte&lt;/em&gt; 4–7, &lt;em&gt;VM&lt;/em&gt; 1, 12, &lt;em&gt;Places in Man&lt;/em&gt; 41, 44, 46, Xenophon &lt;em&gt;Memorabilia&lt;/em&gt; III.ix.14–15; cf. @vlastos1946eap [54–6], @heinimann1961vpt [108, 123–4], @allen1994. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:19&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:20&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;De Arte&lt;/em&gt; 5–6. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:20&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:21&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;At &lt;em&gt;Protagoras&lt;/em&gt; 344c–d, Socrates says misfortune (&lt;em&gt;sumphora&lt;/em&gt;) might incapacitate a craftsman but not an ordinary person (who has no &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; to start with). Here misfortune interferes with &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, but by destroying it, not by preventing it from attaining its goals. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:21&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:22&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Wisdom makes men fortunate in every case [of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;], since I don’t suppose that she would ever make any sort of mistake but must necessarily do right and be lucky—otherwise she would no longer be wisdom.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:22&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:23&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;cf. Allen pp. 85–6. This view, and the thesis that virtue suffices for happiness which it is meant to support, is open to the sorts of objections raised later against the Stoics by Alexander (&lt;em&gt;Supp. De Anima&lt;/em&gt; 160.1 ff.). The argument in the &lt;em&gt;Euthydemus,&lt;/em&gt; is, moreover, clearly fallacious. But the conclusion that virtue is sufficient for happiness is after all Socratic, and the case of &lt;em&gt;De Arte&lt;/em&gt; shows that this position was a contemporary possibility. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:23&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:24&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On stochastics &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; see @allen1994 [88 ff.]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:24&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:25&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;448c; cf. 462a and Aristotle &lt;em&gt;Metaphysics&lt;/em&gt; 981a. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:25&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:26&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;501a. A view of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; according to which it did just consist in experience was influential in later centuries. But quite likely Polus doesn’t himself mean to be defending a peculiar and disputable view of craft (@schiefsky2005 [346–8]). Aristotle mentions Polus’ statement as if it were an unobjectionable truism (&lt;em&gt;Metaphysics&lt;/em&gt; 981a). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:26&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:27&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;cf. &lt;em&gt;VM&lt;/em&gt; 20: doctors know “what the human being is in relation to foods and drinks, and what it is in relation to other practices, and what will be the effect of each thing on each individual.” @dodds1959pg and @irwin1979pg think the use of ‘&lt;em&gt;prospherein&lt;/em&gt;’ at 465a suggests Plato had medicine in mind there too, which is perhaps borne out by 501a. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:27&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:28&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;464a, cf. @irwin1979pg 500e–501a &lt;em&gt;ad loc&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Laches&lt;/em&gt; 189e–190a. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:28&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:29&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cf. @moss2006pai on the relationship between pleasure and illusion in Plato. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:29&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:30&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cf. &lt;em&gt;Euthyphro&lt;/em&gt; 6e, where piety is a &lt;em&gt;paradeigma&lt;/em&gt; or model one may look to. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:30&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:31&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Socrates is as happy with expressions of the form “know X” as “know what X is”—he thinks of knowledge as much in terms of acquaintance or perception as in terms of anything linguistic. See e.g. &lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt; 159a, &lt;em&gt;Euthyphro&lt;/em&gt; 6e, &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; 503e. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:31&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:32&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See, for example, &lt;em&gt;Laches&lt;/em&gt; 190a–c and &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; 503d–e. Indeed a phrase like “knowing X” can simply be used synecdochally to characterize a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; as a whole by reference to its proper object—thus medicine is the “knowledge of health,” or the “knowledge of health and disease” (e.g. &lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt; 165c, &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; []). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:32&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:33&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This sort of test is prominent in &lt;em&gt;Euthyphro,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Laches,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Hippias Major&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:33&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:34&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;p. 149. Though some dialogues, e.g. &lt;em&gt;Charmides,&lt;/em&gt; have the character more of a shared investigation—here it is an idea rather than a purported expert that is being tested. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:34&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:35&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Euthyphro&lt;/em&gt; 16a, &lt;em&gt;Laches&lt;/em&gt; 185b–187b, &lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; 514a–515a. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:35&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:36&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;E.g. in the &lt;em&gt;Ion,&lt;/em&gt; the first third of &lt;em&gt;Gorgias,&lt;/em&gt; and the later parts of &lt;em&gt;Euthyphro&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Laches&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:36&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:37&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cf. @asmith1998 [153]: “too much emphasis has been placed upon the formal features of the Socratic elenchus, and not enough on the purpose and spirit of it.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:37&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:38&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The notion of a “craft analogy” is misleading, as it invites the question “how far does the analogy hold?” But Socrates treats &lt;em&gt;specific&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; as &lt;em&gt;analogues&lt;/em&gt; of virtues, because he thinks that medicine, arithmetic, justice, etc., are &lt;em&gt;all equally&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt;. Contrast Aristotle, who appeals to &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; for a (limited) analogy with virtue, e.g. at &lt;em&gt;NE&lt;/em&gt; 1103a32–b2. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:38&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:39&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Some scholars, such as Terence Irwin, take the analogy to be exact. Others, including Gregory Vlastos and R. E. Allen, think that the analogy has definite limits. David @roochnik1996aaw [6] says that “Plato rejects techne as a model of moral knowledge,” and that Plato juxtaposes &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; and virtue to show how &lt;em&gt;poor&lt;/em&gt; a model &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; provides. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:39&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:40&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Perhaps Socrates objects to the use of the term ‘&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;’? But surely Socrates thinks these Sophists don’t teach virtue at all, not just that it’s not a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; they’re teaching. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:40&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:41&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;@irwin1995pse [198–9] thinks that, for Socrates, &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; are of instrumental value, virtue is &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, and so virtue is of instrumental value. Gregory Vlastos and George Klosko, for example, want to resist that implication, and rightly so. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:41&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:42&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;What about the case of draughts, say? (&lt;em&gt;Petteutike&lt;/em&gt;—&lt;em&gt;Gorgias&lt;/em&gt; 450d; see Dodds &lt;em&gt;ad loc.&lt;/em&gt;: Plato is “probably thinking of a game of pure skill.”) @gosling1978pmt [100] draws attention to flute- and lyre-playing as well. But @roochnik1986 [187–8] goes too far in claiming that Socrates draws a distinction between productive and theoretical crafts at &lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt; 165, so that “the value of theoretical knowledge is not instrumental: its worth derives solely from itself.” (cf. Smith, 137.) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:42&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:43&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is not ultimately a workable position. It identifies the good with knowledge, but to the question what it’s knowledge &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt;, Socrates seems to want to answer that it’s knowledge of the good, which is unilluminating and violates the explicit stricture that a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; have some object independent of itself (&lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt; 165c–166c, &lt;em&gt;Clitophon&lt;/em&gt; 409a–d, &lt;em&gt;Euthydemus&lt;/em&gt; 292a–e, &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; 505b–c). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:43&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:44&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For example @allen1996pih [29]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:44&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:45&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Though the situation in the &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; is more complicated in several ways. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:45&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:46&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As observed just above, they say that &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; can be overwhelmed, but I leave knowledge aside for now. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:46&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:47&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Jessica @moss2006pai argues that pleasure is a trope for practical illusion in Plato. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:47&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:48&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Like most scholars, I don’t believe Socrates really accepts hedonism. But the assumption of hedonism lets Socrates deploy the above argument against &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt; and allows for the development of a sort of toy-model for displaying Socrates’ views. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:48&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:49&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Gorgias,&lt;/em&gt; too, Socrates emphasizes the vulnerability of the ignorant to the manipulation of charlatans who play on their appetites. Cf. also &lt;em&gt;Hippias Minor&lt;/em&gt; 372d–e, &lt;em&gt;Euthyphro&lt;/em&gt; 11b–c, &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; 97c–98b. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:49&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:50&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Although Socrates promises a later consideration of just what this “craft and knowledge” is, he does not bring up the topic again—but perhaps he would intend to qualify the identification with arithmetic, or to say how pleasures and pains are measured? &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:50&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:51&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Thus Terence @penner1997ssk is right to insist that the “knowledge is strong” thesis is not implied by the denial of &lt;em&gt;akrasia.&lt;/em&gt; The denial of &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt; is rather required to ensure we do as knowledge directs. Knowledge is strong because it ensures that you &lt;em&gt;think the right way&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; the denial of &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt; takes over. Cf. also @allen1960sp, pp 257-8 and n. 6. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:51&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:52&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In a sense Socrates refutes the idea that knowledge is weak &lt;em&gt;twice&lt;/em&gt;. If you think of knowledge in terms of knowing the right thing to do on a given occasion, then the refutation does consist in showing that &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt; is impossible. But if we think of knowledge in terms of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, then the refutation is completed only later with the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; of measurement. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:52&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:53&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;cf. &lt;em&gt;Hippias Minor&lt;/em&gt; 265-7. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:53&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:54&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Strictly there is a three-way distinction between 1) the body of knowledge, 2) the possession of the &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;, and 3) the beliefs resulting from &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;.—Hugh @benson2000swm [205–11] also says we should distinguish between knowledge as a &lt;em&gt;dunamis&lt;/em&gt; or power and knowledge as a state which is brought about by that power. But to call Socratic knowledge a &lt;em&gt;dunamis&lt;/em&gt; is to under-describe it—knowledge is not just &lt;em&gt;dunamis&lt;/em&gt; but specifically &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:54&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:55&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; 71a–b, &lt;em&gt;Hippias Minor&lt;/em&gt; 304d–e. Whether Socrates thinks that knowledge of what a thing is is necessary and/or sufficient for knowledge of its qualities or bearers, and how these theses should be understood, has attracted much controversy, mostly under the heading of “the priority of definition.” (A review of construals of, and of evidence for and against, these theses may be found in chs. six and seven of @benson2000swm.) I prefer to ask whether or not it is possible to know anything if you don’t possess a relevant &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:55&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:56&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Richard Kraut suggests that epistemological standards rise over the course of the earlier dialogues—they are lower in the &lt;em&gt;Apology,&lt;/em&gt; for example, and stricter in the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Hippias Major&lt;/em&gt; (@kraut1984sas [xx]. Irwin treats the positive knowledge claims as anomalous and supposes that what Socrates avows is not knowledge but merely true belief (@irwin1977pmt [xx]; cf. @irwin1995pse [28–9]). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:56&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:57&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For instance @brickhouse1994pss [esp. p. 36] say that Socrates disavows systematically reliable knowledge of whole domains; but this is compatible with having knowledge of specific facts, to any degree of certainty or stability, within those domains. (I would say: Socrates has no craft—at least not of a moral sort—but this does not mean that he doesn’t know particular facts which would fall within the purview of some craft.) But this approach leads them to deny that, on the Socratic view, knowledge of definitions is necessary for knowledge of specific facts (45). But you could perfectly well still say exactly that, once you have distinguished different forms of knowledge. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:57&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:58&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Benson p. 237. Though he speaks of understanding rather than &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:58&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:59&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As @woodruff1990pse [77] points out. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:59&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:60&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See Brickhouse and Smith pp. 39–41 for some possibilities (including these two). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:60&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:61&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the same reason, Benson is wrong to suggest that expressions of knowledge which fall outside his expertise sense are “loose” or “in the manner of the vulgar” (236, 238). He worries about cases where disavowals of definitional knowledge are juxtaposed closely with avowals of non-expert knowledge. (He appears—from p. 236 with n. 34—to be thinking of &lt;em&gt;Apology&lt;/em&gt; 29a–b and 37b, and to a lesser extent of &lt;em&gt;Euthydemus&lt;/em&gt; 296e–297a and &lt;em&gt;Hippias Minor&lt;/em&gt; 304e.) He concludes that “we can either take these passages as evidence for another sense of knowledge that Socrates periodically makes use of—although not nearly so frequently as we have been led to suppose—or we can take them as misstatements made in the heat of the moment or in the manner of the vulgar. In either case the account of Socratic knowledge offered in this examination escapes unscathed” (238). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:61&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:62&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This point will be missed if it is not realized that the impossibility of &lt;em&gt;akrasia&lt;/em&gt; and the strength of knowledge are two totally different theses and that neither implies the other. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:62&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:63&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Socrates is actually indifferent here between ‘&lt;em&gt;episteme&lt;/em&gt;’ (352b), ‘&lt;em&gt;phronesis&lt;/em&gt;’ (352c), ‘&lt;em&gt;sophia&lt;/em&gt;’ (352d), and ‘&lt;em&gt;gignoskein&lt;/em&gt;’ (352d). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:63&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:64&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;@lyons1972ssa, chapter 7. Lyons’ discussion concerns the Platonic corpus as a whole. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:64&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:65&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lyons pp. 179, 199 ff. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:65&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:66&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lyons pp. 160–1 ff. &lt;em&gt;Charmides&lt;/em&gt; 159a may be an exception—Socrates observes that Charmides knows Greek, employing ‘&lt;em&gt;epistasthai&lt;/em&gt;,’ but from the &lt;em&gt;Protagoras&lt;/em&gt; I do not think Socrates would speak of a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; of Greek. (Lyons is also of the opinion that Socrates would not consider Greek a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;: see pp. 184–5, 221.) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:66&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:67&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lyons himself discusses a similar case in the &lt;em&gt;Ion&lt;/em&gt; (at 540e) where ‘&lt;em&gt;gignoskein&lt;/em&gt;’ is used in connection with ‘&lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;’ as part of an &lt;em&gt;argument&lt;/em&gt; connecting good judgment in a particular field with an appropriate &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt;: pp. 188–198. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:67&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:68&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;trans. Woodruff with ‘craft’ substituted for his ‘profession.’ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:68&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:69&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cf. @allen1989dpe [326]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:69&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:70&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Though such &lt;em&gt;technai&lt;/em&gt; as arithmetic and measurement show up plenty as well, and &lt;em&gt;take on&lt;/em&gt; practical forms. We might also remember Aristotle’s somewhat disparaging remarks about history, on account of its dealing only with particular facts: &lt;em&gt;Poetics&lt;/em&gt; 1451a36-b11. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:70&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:71&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, Isocrates, in “Against the Sophists,” wants to deny that oratory is a &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; but &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; to claim that it’s worth teaching. In this he is more tolerant than Socrates, and yet it is clear that he is &lt;em&gt;struggling&lt;/em&gt; to characterize this knowledge. Whereas contrast the various forms of knowledge Aristotle tabulates at the start of &lt;em&gt;NE&lt;/em&gt; VI.3. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:71&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:72&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cf. @asmith1998 [157–161]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:72&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:73&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;@woodruff1990pse [81]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:73&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:74&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Woodruff himself allows that the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; is not consistent on the teachability question, and says that the suggestion that there might be knowledge without teachers “is resisted in the balance of the dialogue” (83). The teachability criterion is important as part of the &lt;em&gt;Meno’&lt;/em&gt;s guiding hypothesis that if virtue is knowledge then it will be teachable. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:74&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:75&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In fact a number of familiar features of &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; reappear in the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt;. The completeness requirement seems to show up in Socrates’ insistence that the slave would have to go through many proofs repeatedly before he would have knowledge. The explanatory condition shows up at 98a, as does reliability. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:75&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:76&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;cf. @nehamas1999mps [10–12]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:76&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:77&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This sort of question about expertise is reasonable. It’s no surprise that similar questions show up in contemporary discussions as well. See for instance @goldman2001experts. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:77&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:78&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Unless we are to understand that Socrates himself is an exceptional case. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:78&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:79&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;cf. also &lt;em&gt;Hippias Minor&lt;/em&gt; 372d–e, &lt;em&gt;Euthyphro&lt;/em&gt; 11b–c, &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; 97c–98b. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:79&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:80&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;in Grube’s translation. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:80&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:81&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;At 82b or 84a. Or perhaps properly speaking recollection is what the slave might go on to do, as Nehamas says—@nehamas1999mps, p. 18. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:81&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:82&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The notion of ‘explanation’ in Gail Fine’s proposal that knowledge in the &lt;em&gt;Meno&lt;/em&gt; is justified (roughly: explained) true belief seems to me so expansive as to encourage just this conclusion—that (atomic) knowledge is true belief plus knowledge. [CITE?] &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:82&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:83&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Julia @annas1981ips, p. 192. Annas also mentions the flute example in &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; X and the the jury example in the &lt;em&gt;Theaetetus&lt;/em&gt;. See also Gail @fine2004ktb, p. 43. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:83&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:84&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, Plato also uses the road example to illustrate the difference between knowledge and belief at &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; 506c, and there the example is deployed in an even more off-hand fashion, and is equally out of keeping with the general discussion. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:84&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:85&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In fact the Meno example illustrates a point already familiar from earlier dialogues. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:85&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:86&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Fine does indeed mention this example too. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:86&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:87&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Annas and Fine are looking ahead to disputes about the nature of Plato’s middle-period metaphysics and epistemology. They want to resist too firm a distinction between the intelligible objects of knowledge on the one hand and the sensible objects of belief on the other. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:87&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
